<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An excellent treatise touching the restoring againe of him that is fallen written by the woorthy man Saint Iohn Chrysostome ... ; turned and put into English, out of an ancient Latine translation, written in velume, by R.W. ...</title>
            <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14630.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2155</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23086260</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23086260</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26204</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26204)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1797:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An excellent treatise touching the restoring againe of him that is fallen written by the woorthy man Saint Iohn Chrysostome ... ; turned and put into English, out of an ancient Latine translation, written in velume, by R.W. ...</title>
                  <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
                  <author>Wolcomb, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 143  p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ar. Hatfield for Io. Winnington at the Golden Tunne, neere to S. Dunstans Church in Fleetstreete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Rob. Wolcom[b].</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹²(-A1) B-F¹² G⁵.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26204:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26204:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXCELLENT TREATISE touching the reſtoring againe of him that <hi>is fallen:</hi> Written by the woorthy man Saint <hi>Iohn Chryſostome, Archbiſhop of</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, to Theodorus a friend of his, <hi>who hauing once imbraced the truth of Christs</hi> Goſpell, fell from it by lewd liuing: not vnfit to be read and peruſed by all thoſe, that ſhall be deſirous to ſtir vp, either them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or other being in the like caſe. <hi>Turned and put into Engliſh, out of an</hi> ancient Latine tranſlation, <hi>written in velume:</hi> by R. W.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. <hi>John.</hi> 2, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2.</bibl>
               <p>If any man ſinne, we haue an aduocate with the father, Ieſus Chriſt the iuſt, and he is the reconciliation for our ſinnes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by Ar. Hatfield, <hi>for Io. Winnington at the golden</hi> Tunne, neere to S. Dunſtans <hi>Church in Fleetstreete.</hi> 1588</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:26204:2"/>
            <head>Of the profit of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <l>THe prince of Surgeons, Phoebus ſon,</l>
            <l>In curing famous was:</l>
            <l>Machaon and his brother too,</l>
            <l>By art brought much to pas.</l>
            <l>The best of theſe in festred ſores.</l>
            <l>Did all, and could no more:</l>
            <l>To ſoule of man corrupt by ſinne,</l>
            <l>Their skill denied a dore.</l>
            <l>But heere behold' gainſt dreadful crime.</l>
            <l>A ſoueraigne medcine lies:</l>
            <l>A Moly, Panaceia ſweete,</l>
            <l>To him that vpward flies.</l>
            <l>If fallen downe thou feele deſpaire,</l>
            <l>Read through this pamphlet ſmall:</l>
            <l>It Theôn cheiras, powerfull ſalue,</l>
            <l>In ſuch aſſaults maist call.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Pet. 4, 3.</bibl>
               <p>It is ſufficient for vs that we haue ſpent the time paſt of the life, after the luſt of the Gentils, walking in wantonnes, luſts, droonkennes, in gluttonie, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, and in abominable idolatries.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26204:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull and his eſpeciall good <hi>friend, Maister Iohn</hi> Kemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>horne Eſquier, R. W. wiſheth in <hi>this life proſperous ſucceſſe in all</hi> affaires, and in the life to <hi>come a crowne of</hi> glorie.</head>
            <p>SEeing alwaies it hath been accounted a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous worke, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her to commende in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ollo wiſedome, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ol in Hercules puiſſance, or to praiſe in Minerua knowledge: it may bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hought no leſſe needleſſe or me, to praiſe in fined words and garniſhed ſtile if ſo I were able to do) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our ardent zeal in Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth, and maruellous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection towards the true
<pb facs="tcp:26204:3"/> profeſſors thereof. And bicauſe among thoſe that know you, it ſhineth ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riently, as in words to ſet it foorth, were rather to imbeazle than illuſtrate it; and among thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know you not, by com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mending it abundantly may feare the cenſure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſmoothing, I thinke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> better, at this time (as Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luſt ſaith of Carthage) to ſpeake nothing at all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it than a little. Yet ſurely (though the enuious hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily miſlike it) this I af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firme, when I bethough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to find a meete protecto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for this pamphlet, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might loue it, as Antoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us the Emperor was won<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to loue books, as Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb facs="tcp:26204:3"/> was accuſtomed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the works of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, that might reade it diligently as Eraſmus did Terence, as biſhop Iewell did Horace, as Ladie Iane Graie did Platoes Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: none came to my minde before your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, vnder the wings of whoſe tuition, theſe my ſlender labors might ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſhadowed, from all the malice of ſpitefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouers and taunting carpers. Now concerning the worke, ſome I knowe will finde fault with my preſumption, that being a tender ſuckling and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in good letters, I would dare to put foorth ought in print, eſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:26204:4"/> in ſuch a plentifull time of bookes. Let theſe take this anſwere; that I did it not voluntarily but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, and that by the requeſt, not of one or two but of many, whoſe good will I haue often experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, whoſe friendſhip in the Lorde I will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (for a ſmall cauſe) violate, whoſe authoritie I may not deſpiſe. For lighting by chance on this treatiſe of Chryſoſtome, reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it at the firſt ſight more for antiquitie than ought elſe, aſſoone as I had read it ouer, I did it faithfully for my priuate vtilitie into Engliſh, neuer thinking it ſhould come to this paſſe. But hauing
<pb facs="tcp:26204:4"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent it vnto ſome of my Friends, deſirous of ſuch a peece of matter, they fell ſuddenly into that liking and louing of it, that they neuer ceaſed exhorting, begging, compelling (I may ſay) vntill (maugre my head) I granted, it ſhould go foorth for the benefit of many. Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow being newly borne and come into the world, I beſeech your courteſie to receiue into your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage: and as it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from a willing mind, ſo to take it with a glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome countenance. And notwithſtanding this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of a gratefull mind, do not any waye counterpoiſe the weight
<pb facs="tcp:26204:5"/> of your demerits, yet I beſeech you to accept of the poore widowes mites, and of the cheerfull gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers mind. Thus ſurcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any longer to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt your Worſhips ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affaires, I ſuppliantly craue of the Almightie, daily to augment his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in you and the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentlewoman your wife, that after your rac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ran in this dale of miſery, you may for euer enioi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſight of Chriſt Ieſus in heauen. From Chud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh, Anno. 1587.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips daily and humble Orator,</hi> ROB. WOLCOM<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26204:5"/>
            <head>Of the reſtoring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of him that <hi>is fallen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H,<note place="margin">Ier. 9.1.</note> that my head were (ful) of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; mine eies a fountayne of tears! Much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly is it ſpoken of me now, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t that time, of the Prophet of God.<note place="margin">The worthines and integritie once of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whome he writeth.</note> For howbeit not many ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, neither a whole countrey is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be lamented of me, yet I muſt mourn for a ſoule, of more worth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han many natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of more price <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han many cities.<note place="margin">Ecclus. 16.3.</note> For if one that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe the will of God, be better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han a great companie of the wicked, thou alſo waſt better once, than many multitudes of the Iewes. Wherefore let no man woonder, if I peraduenture vſe more large lamentations at this time,<note place="margin">The cauſe of his lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and powre out more plenty of teares, than at that time the Prophet did. For (as I ſaid) I do
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26204:6"/> not bewaile the ſacking of a citie which is taken, nor the thraldom of the common people little ſet by: but the downefall of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſoule, and the ruine of a temple which Chriſt inhabited. If any euer knew the ornaments of thy minde, which nowe the flame of the diuell hath conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; if any euer beheld the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of thy body, when it glittered with the brightnes of chaſtitie; ſoothly, he would deeme that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the Prophet ſmal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and much inferior: wherein he bewaileth that the hands of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians had prophaned the holy place, and that the enimies fire had deſtroied the Temple, and that the Cherubin and the Arke were defiled, and that the mercy ſeate, with the tables of ſtone, &amp; the golden potte, were polluted For this lamentation which I vſe, is by ſo much more piteous &amp; bitter than the other; by how much more truly and euidently all theſe things were to be ſeene
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26204:6"/> in thy ſoule, than betweene the wals of that Temple; the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which was in thee, was much holier than the other. It ſhined not with the metals of gold and ſiluer, but with the virtues of the mind, &amp; gifts of the holy Ghoſt: fit had within it the Arke &amp; the two Cherubins, that is, the faith of the father, and the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt.<note place="margin">The wretched plight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into this man was fallen.</note> Yet now nought of all theſe is left, all thinges are taken from thy ſoule, ſhe is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft of all her beautie, and all the giftes which God beſtowed on her, ſhe remaineth ſpoiled, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, fowle, ſhe hath loſt all her aide and ſafegard. No dore now is ſhut in her, no entrie is kept, but ſhe lieth open to all naughtie ſpirits, which corrupt the ſoule. No vncleane thought, no filthie deſire is thence expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but if the ſpirite of fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on come, it entreth in, if the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of pride, if the ſpirite of aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, if more helliſh and vnpure, than theſe ſhall come, none for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26204:7"/> them, none beateth them backe. For ſhe hath no kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, no Sexton. And as to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes of heauen there is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe for an vngodlie perſon; ſo at the firſt no infection coulde touch thy mind.</p>
            <p>But perhaps I may ſeeme to ſpeak incredible things, to thoſe eſpecially that knew not thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate, and onely ſee the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction wherein thy ſoule now lieth. This ſurely is the cauſe why I weepe without remedie, bicauſe I knewe thee: and whyd ſorrow vnceſſantly, bicauſe I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member howe long it is, vntill I ſee thee returne to thy wonted and priſtine glorie. Which for all that men may iudge impoſſible, yet to God al things are poſſible.<note place="margin">Mat. 19.26.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 113.8.9. 1. Sam. 2.8.</note> For he it is, that raiſeth the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die out of the duſt, and lifteth vp the poore out of the dunge. That he may ſet him with princes, (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) with the princes of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. He it is that maketh the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren woman to dwell with a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26204:7"/> and a ioyfull mother of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ren.</p>
            <p>Let vs not then doubt nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>paire,<note place="margin">If ſathan draw to ſin, God can pull backe to goodnes.</note> but that thou maieſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onuerted into a better caſe. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the diuell could do ſo much in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee, as to draw thee from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eight of vertue to the depth of wickednes, how much more ſhal God be able to reclaime thee to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he higheſt pitch of goodnes, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot onely make thee that thou waſt once, but far more bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han thou diddeſt ſeeme in thy owne conceit. Onely be of ſtout courage, neither caſt off the hope of goodnes: let not, I pray thee, that betide thee, which doth the godleſſe.<note place="margin">Vngodlines without peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie breedeth to deſpaire.</note> It is impietie not the multitude of ſins, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ringeth a foole to deſperation: and therfore Salomon ſaid not, that each one when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth into the depth of euils contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but,<note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 18, 3.</note> the wicked (ſaith he) if he come into the depth of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils contemneth.<note place="margin">Or, when the wicked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth contempt</note> It is then a point of the impious to haue no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26204:8"/> hope of ſaluation, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne when they come into the depth of ſinnes, vngodlines not permitting them to haue reſpect to God, and to returne thither from whence they fell. So that this thoght which cutteth away all hope of conuerſion, iſſueth from impiety, and as a moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uie ſtone accloying the ſoule, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perpetually compelleth it to be hold the earth and neuer to loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpward on God.<note place="margin">When we ſin we must not deſpaire.</note> But a luſtie ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macke and loftie minde will caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> downe this hurtful weight of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule, and tread vnder feete Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than, that being his owne gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour he may ſing the Pſalmiſt wordes to God,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 113, 2.</note> As the eies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeruants looke vpon the hands o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their maſters, and as the eies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a maiden vpon the hands of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſtres: ſo our eies waite vpon the Lord our God, till he haue mercy vpon vs. Haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, O Lord, haue mercy vpon vs, for we haue ſuffered to much contempt. And in theſe word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26204:8"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this heauenly prophecy, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſingular doctrine, we haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered too much comtempt. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that he woulde haue vs ſaie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat although for the multitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f our ſins we haue ſuffred much contempt, and are ſurrounded with reproches, yet our eies ſhal waite vpon the Lord our God til we haue mercy vpon vs, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will not leaue of beſeeching, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntill we be vouchſafed forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es.<note place="margin">We ought to be earneſt in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when we ſue for forgiuenes, and not to rest till God haue fulfilled our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions.</note> For this is the badge of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſtant and ſetled minde, that is not weary of perſeuering in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> treaty through deſpaire to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain, but continueth &amp; perſiſteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n crauing, vntill the Lord haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ercy vpon it.<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe two pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods following G. F. Capito hath not in his tranſlation.</note> And leaſt you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould thinke you offend greatly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore the Lord, if not vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to be heard, you continue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mportunately in praiers, call to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emorie the euangelicall para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, and there you ſhal find, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord ſheweth, that ſtiffe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſeuering beggers are not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cceptable to him. For he ſaith,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26204:9"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 11, 8.</note> Though he would not giue hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bicauſe he is his friend, yet b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe of his importunitie, he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> riſe, and giue him aſmuch as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> needeth. Vnderſtand therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (deare friend) that the diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> putteth into our minds deſpai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of obteining, to this end, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may cut from vs the hope of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> goodnes of God, which is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ancor of our ſaluation, the fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation of life, the guide of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way through which we paſſe heauen: in briefe, the Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8, 24.</note> by hope we are ſaued. ſo much that our ſaluation co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth in hope, which draweh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſoules from out the eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knit (as it were) to certain chaines hanging downe fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heauen, and calleth again the to the heauenly dwelling pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which cleaue to themſelues, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alting them ſecurely aboue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> troubles of this life, and earth miſeries. Wherefore if any e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumbred with theſe calamitie be diſſolute, and let go out of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:26204:9"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>andes the ancor of hope, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt needes fall, and be carried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the bottomleſſe pit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nditie of euils.<note place="margin">The dangers of deſpaire.</note> Which aſſoone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the enimie ſhall perceiue, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee vs loath the multitude of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, &amp; feare through remorſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſcience, ſtraight way he dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth neere, and caſteth before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur eies cogitations of deſpaire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore heauie than any lead or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rauel: which if we vndertake, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt of neceſſitie be drowned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he depth of euils, bicauſe, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he very loade, the ſtaies of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aluation are broken. Into the which depth bicauſe thou art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt, thou doeſt throwe behinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee the precepts of a good and gentle lord, and thou doeſt obey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he becke of a bloudie and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles tyrant, the enimie of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aluation. Thou haſt ſhaken off the ſweete yoke of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 11, 30.</note> &amp; haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid on thy necke for it, the hard and iron fetters of ſinne: thou haſt ſhaken off the eaſie burden of a lowly and meeke Lord, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26204:10"/> for it haſt ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged about thy nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a milſtone, but howe long doe thou ſo continue? Stand now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the laſt, and ceaſe to drowne th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnhappy ſoule, without any car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without any aduiſe: howe lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doeſt thou haſte it foorth, &amp; ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it downe headlong to thy own decaie?<note place="margin">Luke. 15.</note> And truly the woman the Goſpell, which found again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the loſt groate, called togith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her friends and neighbours, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſhould reioice with her: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I will call your and my friends neighbours togither, and wil e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> treate them to meete, not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſhoulde be glad, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſhould lament with me: no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they ſhoulde reioyce, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mourne with me, and greatly ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe, lifting vp their handes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heauen, as they ſhall ſee me t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doe, and I will ſaye vnto them howle and lament with me, ô m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> friendes, powre out and bring foorth with me fountaines an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> floudes of teares, not for that haue loſt vnpoiſable weights o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:26204:10"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lde, or innumerable talents of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er; not becauſe I haue loſte reads full of coſtly pearles, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that my friend<note n="*" place="margin">Amicus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ipſe.</note> dearer than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y golde, &amp; more pretious than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſtone, is (I knowe not how) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ile he ſailed with vs ouer the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge and broade ſea of this life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en downe into the very depth deſtruction. And if ſome one my friends ſhall goe about to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mfort, and will me to leaue of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rowing, I will aunſwere him in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Prophets words:<note n="*" place="margin">Or, let me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, I will weepe bitterly, you can not comfort me.</note> Suffer me weepe moſt bitterly, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de on comforting mee: for I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epe not through the affection the fleſh, neither is my lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion woman like, wherein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are immoderate teares to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med. I mourne for that, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e great and famous Apoſtle S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ule ſaieth he mourneth for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en as he ſaieth:<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 12, 22.</note> That I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourne for them that haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and haue not repented.</p>
            <p>Certes with reaſon ſhall one buke thoſe that for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin">The death of the ſoule is piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, ſeeing the death of the body is ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly taken.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26204:11"/> death of their friends we without meane; but when t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wounds not of a bodie but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule are lamented, and of ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule, which in death it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſheweth ſignes of hir former be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, and wonderous gaines, a with liuely tokens diſplayeth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> floure of vertues extinguiſhed hir, who is ſo cruell, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quainted with vertue, that wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not be mooued to lamentati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that would not be prouoked teares? For as it is a pointe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> philoſophy, to forbeare weep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for common death: ſo in a death of a ſoule, and ſuch a ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to receiue comfort, I adiud both vngodly and irreligious. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ordinary death to keepe the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from teares, is the chiefeſt thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the ſtudie of wiſedome: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how ſhall not he ſeeme to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented for without intermiſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who of late reckned the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brauenes of the bodie but li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> carued ſtones, who account gold as clay, who reſpected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:26204:11"/> lights as durt, and now atra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed by the ſodaine feuers of luſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d voluptie, being depriued of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e integritie and bewtie of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inde, hath ſhaken hands with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rtue, and is become a ſlaue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce and pleaſure? This man ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot bewaile? This man ſhall I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t moyſten ſo long with a riuer teares, vntill with weeping I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r vp feeling in him, and by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmth of teares I raiſe ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely motions in him, if mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng may do ought? And if mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs of the body ceaſe not from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>menting, though they aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know, their weeping profite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em nothing, to renew the life him that is dead: why ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t we, that know the ſoule may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> called from death by conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n, earneſtly follow after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edicine of repentance, that (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n the ſepulchre being opened) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th abundance of teares he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay be recouered? Yea alſo I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inke we are to be accuſed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ggardie, ſith the lamenters of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26204:12"/> bodies and ordinarie death o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weepe ſo much and continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (yet certaine, as we ſaid, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they ſhall not raiſe againe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dead,) if we that know, that repentance (lamentation cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led with it) a ſoule may be ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to his former ſtate, (for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kingly prophet ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal 6, 5.</hi> Or, in the graue who ſhal praiſe thee.</note> In hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhall confeſſe thy name?) do thing ſo.</p>
            <p>We know too, that diuers the daies both of vs and our a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſtors hauing ſliden out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtraight path, and ſtraied fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the entrance of the narrow w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were ſo againe reſtored, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their end anſwered their beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, obtaining the goale a crowne, yea they were thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to haue place among the nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of the Saints. But as long one remaineth in the flame a fornace of luſt, theſe thing ſeem impoſſible to him althou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="*" place="margin">A thouſand.</note> infinit examples ſhould be al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged. But if ſome ſmall conuerſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be began, and the penitent po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26204:12"/> caſt vpward his eies, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourning flame will tarry behind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, and by how much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wiftly he ſhall take his pace, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o much more, before him ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſee all things ſumpled with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e coale of an heauenly dew.<note place="margin">Deſpaire the greatest enimy to our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> So much woorth is it that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of one thing, the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nimy to our ſaluation, to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onuerſion, to our repentance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o wit deſperation: which if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake hold in our mind, how great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſire ſoeuer we haue of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, how great purpoſe ſoeuer to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue euerlaſtingly, if (I ſay) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>paire come, all the entry to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation is ſtopped, the way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entance is hindered, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eginning of anguiſh is engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red. And how then ſhal he, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s out of the way, and to whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he doore is ſhut, be able to doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny good worke, when as (bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſe deſpaire prohibiteth) he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annot come to the entrance of goodnes? For this cauſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell goeth about with tooth and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26204:13"/> naile, to plant in our harts ſuch manner of cogitations. For i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the feare of deſpaire ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue vs from the way of ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue, he hath no long combate with vs, for why ſhould he aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſault when none reſiſteth? An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whoſo ſhall haue the power to vndoe this knot, incontinent hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength returneth, the luſtine of his mind encreaſeth, he ſhal b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> delighted with the renuing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe contentions, the reaſon is he ſhall ſee himſelfe chaſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chaſer, &amp; purſue the perſecute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And if in caſe, (as in wraſtling i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> falleth out) he faulter againe &amp; fal, let him not be out of hope fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhame, but remember, that is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the law of wreſtling and iuſting not once to fall, (for he may no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be ſaid to be conquered that fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth) but in the end not to yeeld for he that deſpaire hath may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtered, howe can he either reco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer might in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention, or with ſtand and fight, ſeeing he taketh his heeles, and doth not at al re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26204:13"/> to the conflict? Neither thinke that I ſpeake of thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonely, that haue tranſgreſſed in ſmall and not much important things, but my ſpeech is of him that hath made himſelfe a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine to all miſchiefe, and hath damned to himſelfe the way to the kingdome of heauen, &amp; was once of the number not of the incredulous miſcreants, but of them that liked God, and after this hath fallen either into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, or into all ſortes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſtitie, which (as the Apoſtle ſaith.)<note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.3.</note> to name is vnſeemely. This man (I ſaye) ought not to miſdoubt of ſaluation, though ſuch wickednes enuiron him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the laſt gaſpe.<note place="margin">The anger of God is not paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore though we ſinne, yet his wrath may be changed into mercie.</note> But harken what the cauſe of this is. If the wrath of God were an affection that did worke a paſſion, wee might rightly ſay, that the flame of it kindled with ſo many &amp; ſuch euils, might not bee quenched: but for aſmuch as the truth tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that the nature of God is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26204:14"/> void of paſſions, we muſt learne that though God puniſh, though he plague, he doth it not with a wrathfull paſſion, but with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable gentlenes, going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to cure vs, not to confound vs, and therefore with gladnes will receiue the penitent. For the plaiſter of repentance (if thou ſeeke it) healeth the ſoule, and defendeth thee from the anger of God, which he conceiued for thine offences. God doth not (as I ſaide) puniſhe a ſinner for his owne fantaſie,<note place="margin">Why God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth man.</note> when he reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his wrong, (for the nature of God is not capable of ſuch an affection) but for our profit; he doth all things for our vtilitie, &amp; he chaſtiſeth and correcteth not to auenge himſelfe, but to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vs.</p>
            <p>And if any perſiſt in hardnes, as the man that turneth his eies from the light, damnifieth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the light, but damneth himſelfe to darkenes; ſo he that contemneth vertue through a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26204:14"/> hart that can not repent, eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth himſelf from ſaluation. And as a Phyſition that ſuffreth wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at the hands of phrenticke and braineſicke men, ſorroweth not, nor is diſpleaſed a whit at it, but doth all things that appertaine to eaſe the maladie of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, (for the wrong is cauſed by paine:) and as you may ſee the Phyſition glad at a litle amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſicke perſon, and to execute the reſidue of his charge with ioye and chearefulnes, not keeping in mind the wrong don, but reſpecting the health of the patient: ſo, much rather God,<note place="margin">God is willing to haue vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</note> when we are become ſtark wood, is not greedy of vengeance for our treſpaſſes, but deſirous to heale our olde &amp; putrified biles; for to this end he ſaith and doth al things, thirſting after our ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not our puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And albeit reaſon ſufficiently ſhew the contrary, yet leaſt you ſhould ſtagger in the matter, we are able to auouche it out of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26204:15"/> holie Scriptures. Tell me what more wicked bodie was there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer than the king of Babylon? Who hauing found out in many things the omnipotency of God, in ſo much that hee worſhipped his Prophet,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.46.</note> and commaunded frankencenſe and myrrhe to be offred to him: yet againe in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of God he returned to his wonted hawtines,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> and did caſt iointly into the ouen of burning fire, thoſe that refuſed to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip his image, bicauſe they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the ſeruice of God. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, God allured to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and gaue occaſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canting to this ſo bloudie, ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked a king. Firſt in this, that with the three children he appeared vnto him in the ouen;<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> afterward, in that he cauſed him to ſee the viſion which Daniel interpreted,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.</note> that was able to mollifie euen an hart of flint. But when he was warned by workes, the Prophet alſo exhorted him by wordes, &amp; he receiued the counſell of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26204:15"/> Prophet, ſaying:<note place="margin">Dan. 4.</note> Wherefore, O king, let my counſell be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto thee, and breake off thy ſins by righteouſnes, and thine iniquities by mercie towards the poore, lo, let there be an healing of thine errour.</p>
            <p>What ſaieſt thou to this, O thou wiſe and bleſſed man? Yet is there a returning after ſo great ſlides? credit me there is, after grieuous ſickenes and from the doore of death proceedeth health, and after deſperate ſins many waxe wiſe. For loe (as we ſhewed afore) this king of Babel had now ſtopped all way of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, in that he prouoked the Lord to wrath, who made him, and exalted him to the throne of a kingdome, who reuealed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to him heauenly myſteries, who imparted on him the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things to come, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed to him the ſecrets of all his kingdome, who confounded by the diuine ſolution of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the iuglings of the wiſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26204:16"/> men, Aſtrologers, Gazarens, &amp; Caldeans, and opened to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie of a child, by a diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation a hidden ſecrete: in ſomuch that he ſeemed not only to beleeue in the higheſt God, but to proclaime throughout all the world, that the God of Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell was the true God; yet after this, he fell into ſuch an outrage, that he threw headlong into the hoate burning ouen the ſeruants of God that would not worſhip his image. And yet ne here doth the mercy of God forget to cure and remedy him, but in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the fire, when he had put to the flame the children that worſhipped God, there he aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth him not with quenching the fire with water, but with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a wonder. For he could both extinguiſh the fire, &amp; diſtill down a ſhowre from heauen, but this he doth not, leaſt he ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the force of his rage, but permitteth the flame to be made as great, as the furie of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26204:16"/> deſired, and he doth not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him to puniſh, but taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way power from the torment. And that no one that ſawe the children not burnt, might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it was a vaine imagination, no fire in deede that he ſaw, he ſuffred the executioners (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe that ſtoode about the fornace) to be conſumed, that he might make manifeſt, that not onely fire in truth was ſeene, but that Gods commandement was more forcible than anie ſtrength of fire. For euery thing that is, obeieth him of whome it had his beginning. That fire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the bodies of thoſe ſaints and by the ordinance and wil of God forgetting his nature wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it burneth, vpon it ſhewed onely his nature of illumining, rendring againe the holie and faithfull thing committed to his charge nothing hurted; for they came foorth out of the flaming fornace as it had beene out of a princes palace, woorthy to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26204:17"/> admired of all, of all to be reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced. None then caſt his eies on the king who glittered in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with a diademe on his head, but he was forſaken of all a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though he had beene no bodie, for that the children had rapt euerichone into an admiration. For who woulde not be aſtonied that the fire was afrighted at the fight of the yoong mens bodies, and that it did not onely flie from the fleſh of thoſe ſaints, but alſo did not touch one haire of their head (which was but little) nor the vttermoſt hem of their garments?</p>
            <p>Who would not admire, that their members were ſtronger than mountains, their garments than metals, their haires than diamondes? And herein is the woonder aggrauated, that when they were in the middeſt of the fire, they ſang a Pſalme to God, albeit experience teacheth, that they that are committed to the flame, be conſumed aſſoone as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26204:17"/> they open their mouth. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, thoſe bleſſed children re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine with God glorious, with men woonderful; but the naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie king was neither mooued with theſe miracles, nor woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at the viſion and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling of his confuſion, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode heard of beliefe, neither yet was puniſhed. And hitherto Gods patience was not tired, but when he had forborne him a long time, at length he vnneth corrected him, not puniſhing the offences paſt, but reſpecting the amendment to come: in a word, he condemned him not euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly, but chaſtiſed for a little ſpace,<note place="margin">Dan. 4, 33.</note> but reformed for a fewe yeeres, he got againe his former eſtate, ſo that by the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ſuſtained no loſſe, but by the amendement gat great good.</p>
            <p>Such (beleeue me) ſuch is the goodnes of God towards men, neuer reiecting repentance if it be truely and vprightly offered;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26204:18"/> although one come to the top of wickednes,<note place="margin">Nunquam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a eſt ad bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos mores via. Sen.</note> notwithſtanding if he haue a deſire to returne to the way of vertue, he gladly reteineth and imbraceth him, and doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things whereby he may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed to his wonted conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yea, and that which is more worth the noting, although any be not able wholy to abandon the vre of ſin, he will not refuſe how ſmall ſoeuer repentance, and in how little time ſoeuer vndertaken, he will take it, and not ſuffer the leaſt conuerſion goe vnreguerdoned. For this (me thinketh) Iſaiah ſheweth,<note place="margin">Iſ. <hi>57.</hi> Or, for his ſins, J haue made him ſory a litle while, &amp;c. and J haue beene ſad, and I haue walked heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and J haue healed him, J haue comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.</note> where he ſpeaketh after this manner of the people of the Iewes, for his ſin I haue made him ſomewhat ſory, and I haue ſmitten him, and I haue turned my face from him, and he was ſory and walked heauily, and I healed him, and comforted him.</p>
            <p>But the wicked king, that by reaſon of the naughtines of his wife ſought a booty for his luſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26204:18"/> may be a more euident teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of this matter; who being troubled with the hainouſnes of his ſins repented, and cloathed in ſackcloth bewailed his doing, and here in ſo drew the mercy of God vpon him, that he pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all his treſpaſſes. For ſo it is ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">1. King. 21, 28.29.</note> and the word of the Lord came to Eliah the Tiſhbite, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeeſt thou how Ahab is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled before me? bicauſe he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth himſelfe before me, I will not bring that euill in his daies. Alſo after him againe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes, who bare the bell from all pittiles tyrants, who ouerthrew the ſeruice of God and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his lawes, who repleniſhed the temple of the Lord with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, thruſting out the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Lord, this king (I ſay) ſurpaſſing the wickednes that euer hath beene heard of, albeit repented, and after was numbred among the friends of God.<note place="margin">2. Chron. 33.</note> Now if he or they of whom afore we mentioned, pondering
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26204:19"/> the vnmeaſurablenes of the tranſgreſſions, had deſpaired o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> returne by conuerſion &amp; repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance, doubtles they had loſt a thoſe good things which hape<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned vnto them by amendmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of life. But contrariwiſe they be holding the mercie that canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be vttered, and God his infini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and profound goodnes, vntie from their neckes the diueli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bonds of deſpaire, &amp; ſpurring v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelues, were conuerted t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the way of vertue, and by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing their foote from head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long ruine finiſhed a good courſe. And ſo far of the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the holy men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 95, 1.</note>Now harken how God by the prophet allureth vs in wordes to repentance, to day (ſaith he) if you will heare his voice, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den not your harts, &amp;c. And in that he ſaith to day, he meaneth all our life time,<note place="margin">Short repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance looſeth not reward.</note> euen vnto the laſt part (if ſo it chance) of our old age; for not the length of time but the trunes of repenting
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26204:19"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s conſidered, or elſe how is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead that the Niniuites in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itle ſpace of one day not in long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime purged a moſt grieuous ſin.<note place="margin">Ionas. 3.</note> And the theefe alſo which han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the croſſe,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.</note> needed not a very long ſeaſon to be made fit for paradiſe, but ſo much ſpace was ynough as was ſpent in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing one ſpeech. Inſomuch that in a moment, hauing all his ſinnes clenſed, he was thought woorthy to enter heauen before euen the Apoſtles. And ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, do we not oftentimes ſee the martyrs in one day, and percaſe in the ſpace of one hower, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the crownes of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards? Wherefore hardines is al, and a boldnes conioined with prompt and ready minds, that mooued (as it were) with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain wrath, we be diſpleaſed with luſt our inueagler, and offer all our deſire and loue on the altar of vertue. For this is that thing that God willeth, and requireth of vs, he ſeeketh not continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26204:20"/> of time, nor vexations of vs, he reſpecteth true and vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned conuerſion<note n="*" place="margin">Seeing many that were last, haue by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest labour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thoſe that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</note>. It is not then ſo bad to fall, as after a fall to ly ſtill, and be vnwilling to riſe, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the vitiouſnes of our ill intent (taking no delight but in ſin) with deſperate ſpeeches. For wtih indignation the prophet crieth out againſt theſe; Doth not he riſe vp that falleth, and he returne that is turned away<note place="margin">Ierem. 8.</note>?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Godly men may riſe by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance after their fall.</note>Now if thou ſay; What if one of the faithfull ſhould fall, may he be reſtored? To this I anſwer; in that we ſay he hath fallen, we confeſſe he ſtood before he fell: for it is an abſurd thing to bee ſpoken, that any man fell, that hath ſtill lien and neuer ſtood. We will produce alſo out of the booke of God allegations, if ought hath been ſpoken of this matter, either in parables or in plaine ſpeeches, or if any thing may be found in the examples of our elders. What repreſenteth that ſheepe,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> which when it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26204:20"/> from the ninetie and nine, was ſought by the ſheepheard, and brought home on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? doth it not euidently ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſliding and the repairing of a faithfull bodie? For it was a ſheepe like as were the ninetie and nine, not of any other, but of the ſelfe ſame flocke, it had the ſelfe-ſame guider, it was firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in the ſame paſture, with the ſame water, and the ſame fold contained it that did the reſt. But it ſtraied not a little, &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred through the mountaines and hils, that is, it went far from the right path, yet the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hepheard ſuffereth it not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine away in ſtraying, but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth it, and calleth it againe, and be calleth it home, not driuing it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iolently, neither beating it with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rokes, but ſupporting it with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is owne ſhoulders. For as all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kilfull phyſitions by mitigation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f medicine deale more nicely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd tenderly, with thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue been long vexed with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26204:21"/> ſo God doth not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claime thoſe that haue been long corrupt with ſinne to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way of vertue with any tariand at all, but by peece-meale, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> little and little, bearing wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their weakenes in many thing and aſſiſting them often, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conuerſion on the ſudden ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not be vnpleaſant to them, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they may not go againe lewdnes, for the difficultie of r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turning.</p>
            <p>But not this parable only d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clareth the moderatenes of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teration,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> but that likewiſe whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is written of the prodigal ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> He was a ſonne alſo no a lia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his naturall brother that ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> went from his father: he (I ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was a ſonne that went far in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> borders of iniquitie: for he we into a far countrie, and far fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord, he that was rich an of good name, was made baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than a ſeruant and hireling, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſorrowfully returning, he was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken into his ancient eſtate, an
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26204:21"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueſted in his former glorie. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow if he had loſt hope, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d beene aſhamed to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne to his father, bicauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> miſchances, and had abode way in a ſtrange and forren <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>untrie, he had not gotten that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gat, but periſhing for want of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, had died a miſerable deth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u ſee therefore how great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſitie repentance hath, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce in turning hope hath, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>entance the prodigall ſonne couered the old condition of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e glory, which the elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er had without repentance. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d if I might ſpeake that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould in theſe matters, me ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth he gat more by conuerſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an the other had.<note place="margin">verſe. 29, 30.</note> For ſo he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mſelfe ſaith, loe theſe manie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eres haue I done thee ſeruice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d yet thou neuer gaueſt me a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d that I might make mery with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y friends.<note place="margin">Sinners con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted get more than they which ſtumbled not.</note> But when this thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nne was come, which hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ured thy goods with harlots, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou haſt for his ſake killed the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26204:22"/> fat calfe. Why ſhould I not the thinke, that he that turneth b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> repentance obteineth more th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other, ſith he had neuer a kid g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen him, but for this the fat cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was killed? Wherefore beloue hauing theſe examples of repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance, let vs not perſiſt in euil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor deſpaire of attonement: h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will neuer (put affiance in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> turne his eies from the conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, if we our ſelues remoue n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſelues from God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hier. 23, 23.</hi> Our ſinnes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate vs from God. <hi>Iſai. 59, 2.</hi>
               </note> For h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaith, I am a God at hand, an not a God far off. And againe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the prophet,<note n="*" place="margin">Or, your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities haue ſeparated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene you and your God.</note> Your ſins ſepara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> betweene me and you. If the our ſinnes diſſeuer vs from God let vs take away this bar, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing may let vs to be brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into the fauor of God.</p>
            <p>Will you that I ſhew it not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpoken in parables, but forme in deed? There was a man a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong the Corinthians by a likelihood of no ſmall calling, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had committed ſuch a ſin as wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted amongſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tils,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26204:22"/> being of the number of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aithfull, and Chriſt his frindes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſome reporte (me thinketh) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he was of the linage of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rieſts. What then? Paul neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arted him from the number of thoſe, that hope to attaine ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation. But when he had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntly rebuked the Corinthians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or him, purpoſing to ſhew that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here is no wound nor diſeaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat may not be cured and made whole by repentance,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5, 5.</note> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth to deliuer him ouer vnto Sathan, for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirite may be ſaued in the day of the Lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſus. But this he commaundeth before he was done to wit of his repentance;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2, 6.</note> for when he had ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, it is ſufficient (ſaith he) to him,<note place="margin">8.</note> that he hath bene rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of many, and addeth, Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I praye you that you would confirme your loue towardes him:<note place="margin">11.</note> leſt Sathan ſhould circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent vs, for we are not ignorant of his enterpriſes. The nation of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26204:23"/> the Galathians after it had pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectly beleued in Chriſt, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receiued the holy Ghoſt, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much that it wrought ſignes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miracles by the ſpirite, after, the faith of Chriſt it had ſuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned many things, after all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thinges (I ſay) it fell from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faith, and was renued againe the exhortations of the Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> And that thou maiſt knowe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the ſpirit they had done wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders and miracles, heare ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Gal. 3, 5.</note> he therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that miniſtreth to you the ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and worketh miracles amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you, doeth he it by the works the lawe, or by the hearing faith preached? And againe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they had ſuſteined many thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after the receit of faith, he teſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fieth where he ſaith:<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> Haue yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffred ſo many things in vaine Nowe after ſo great a ſteppe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faith, they committed a ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which was able to abaliena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them from Chriſt, of which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle himſelfe ſaith:<note place="margin">Gal. 5, 2.</note> Behol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:26204:23"/> Paul ſay vnto you, that if you be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ircumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou nothing. And againe,<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer are iuſtified by the lawe, ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re fallen from grace. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding after theſe ſlydes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n faith, after ſo grieuous a fall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e reclaimeth them, and (as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay ſay) with motherlike com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſion reformeth them, ſaying: My little children,<note place="margin">Gal. 4, 19.</note> of whome I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rauell in birth againe, vntill Chriſt be formed in you. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſe therefore by all this is there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aught, but that it may be, that Chriſt may be formed anewe in him, that hath ſold himſelfe to worke iniquitie,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18, 32</note> for he will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he death of a ſinner, but that he ſhoulde be conuerted and liue. For this cauſe (moſt intirely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oued) let vs goe about to fulfill the will of God, therefore hath God created vs, and cauſed vs to be that we were not,<note place="margin">Heauen was made for man, hell for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils.</note> that he maye beſtowe euerlaſting good things vpon vs, and enfranchiſe vs into the heauenly citie, for he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26204:24"/> made vs not faggots for hell fire The kingdom of heauen was or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deined for vs, and hell for the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell. And that this is true, the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpell reacheth: for the Lord ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay to them on his right hand Come ye bleſſed of my father,<note place="margin">Mat. 25, 34.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herite ye the kingdome prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red for you from the foundation of the world.<note place="margin">Verſ. 42.</note> But he ſhall ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them on his left hande, depa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from me ye curſed into euerla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſting fire, which is prepared fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the diuell and his angels. By thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſon, the kingdome of heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was made for man, and hell f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for the diuell, euen from the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation of the world.</p>
            <p>So much doth it concerne vs that by perſeuering in euils, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doe not frowardly exclude o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſelus from the entrance of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">Repentance in this life profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth much, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life nought.</note> And while we are in this life how great ſoeuer ſins we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, it is poſſible by repentance to purge them: but when we are once dead, then though we ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (and we ſhall be very ſorrie)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26204:24"/> yet there will be no profite of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Although there be gnaſhing of teeth, although there be howling &amp; lamenting, although we pray and beg with innumerable petitions, yet none ſhall heare vs, none ſhall helpe vs, no not our toong tormented in flames ſhall be wet with the tip of a finger dipped in water. But we ſhall heare that which the rich man heard of Abraham, that there is a great ſwallowing pit ſet betweene vs and you,<note place="margin">Luk. 16, 26.</note> ſo that they which would go from hence to you can not: neither can they come from thence to vs. Therefore let vs repent (my brother) and as good and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruants ſeeke our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, neither let vs be diſcouraged to obtaine pardon (while we liue here) by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for in hell (as I ſaide) the medicines of repentance wil not be auaileable, but in this life, though in the end of your daies and extreeme old age you vſe it,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26204:25"/> it ſhall cure you. Which to ſtop the diuell ſturreth &amp; laboreth, that he may make vs deſpaire, for he knoweth that euen in a little time, if any be penitent though it be a ſhort turning, yet it will not be vnfruitefull. For as the man that giueth a cup of cold water looſeth not his meed; ſo he that hath remorſe for his euill deedes, though his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſeeme not counterpoiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his offences, yet how little ſoeuer it be, and in the twinkling of an eie, the recompence ſhall not be lacking. No one good deed though very ſmal, ſhall be contemned of the Lorde a iuſt iudge: for if he be ſo hard a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putiſt of our miſdeeds, as that euery one muſt be puniſhed for his wordes and thoughts,<note place="margin">Matt. 12.</note> how much more ſhall our good deeds both great and ſmall be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the day of doome? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou thinke it vnpoſſible to be reſtored to thy accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med order of life, yet prune off a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26204:25"/> little from that great extremitie of ryot and luſt, which thou ſhalt perceiue not a whit vnfructu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Make only a beginning and ſmooth the way to goodnes, which tread, albeit with the tips of thy toes; and till thou begin, the way of vertue ſeemeth diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile and harde. For ſuch is the nature of all things, that all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is thought greeuous while it is weighed onely in our minds, but when we come to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and haue ouercommed ſome of the worke, then all feare and fainting is ſhaken off, and the ſucceſſe of the worke breedeth delight: ſo alſo the renuing of vertue cauſeth gladnes to the mind, and then are we ſtronger, when we ſee the hope of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on approch.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe alſo the enimie tooke Iudas hence, leaſt in caſe knowing there was a returne to ſaluation, he might reforme his fall by repentance. And I ſay not (although it be wonderfull) that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26204:26"/> that ſinne of Iudas might not be purged by repentance: for which cauſe I intreat and beg o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thee that thou abandon out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy minde all diueliſh cogitati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, and quickly beturne thee to the way of ſaluation. If I ſhould ſodainly and wholy call thee to that old height of vertue, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mighteſt not without cauſe tremble, not without deeme i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> harde. But conſidering this one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly I deſire at thy handes, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou increaſe not in iniquities neither euery day go neerer t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perdition, that thou leaue off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make an end of offending, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doſt thou doubt and linger drawing backe thy foote, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fear only to receiue the though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of goodnes? Hath not the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluitie of luſt bred loathſomnes, as yet in thee?<note place="margin">Pleaſure of the bodie vadeth away.</note> What hath it bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered them that abode in bodily ſenſualitie and in the pleaſure of this preſent life vntill the end of their liues? Looke now on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their ſepulchers, and ſee whethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:26204:26"/> there be any ſhew of glorious io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>litie? Whether there be any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of dainties and ſumptuous fare. Demaund where now their gorgeous weedes and ſtrange perfumes be, whither the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their games, the troupes of their attendants, the dainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their feaſts is gone? Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their laughtures, ſports, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate and vnbrideled luſt is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecome and vaniſhed? Where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey themſelues are with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe things? What was the end of them both? Behold more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly and come more neere to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir graues, looke on the duſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nely and the filthy reliques of wormes, remember that this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he end of bodies, although in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elights and ioy, although in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our and chaſtitie men ſpend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir life. And would God all the matter were ended in duſt and wormes, theſe loffes would ſeem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut little, and the ſtate of nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought eaſily be excuſed. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow glid thine eies from theſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:26204:27"/> aſhes and graues,<note place="margin">How terrible the iudgement ſeate of God ſhall be to the wicked.</note> and thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that horrible ſeate of the iudgement of God, which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed with a burning riuer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fiery ſtreames, where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, wherei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vtter darkenes, where is that worme of conſcience that neuer dieth, and the vnquenchable fire. Forget not the parable of Lazarus and the rich man,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> who being once an owner of grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wealth, and clad in purple and ſilke, could not find (afterward) one drop of water, &amp; that when he was in the heate of the fire. Tell me (I beſeech thee) what is there in this life but a dreame?<note place="margin">Our life but a dreame.</note> For as thoſe that are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to liue among metals, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with any other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they take ſome reſt after the hard labours of their troubleſome life, beleeue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to enioy the manifold dainties they ſee before them; but when they ariſe they feele full well, there is nothing left of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26204:27"/> the delicatenes of the dream, ſo that rich man who in a dreame had the voluptuouſnes of this life, when he deceaſed, nought remained with him, but griefe of the things paſt, &amp; paine of the things preſent. Remember this (my friend) and oppoſe hell fire to this flame of luſt and concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence that now tormenteth thee. And it is a ſtrang kind of medicine that fire ſhould be quenched by fire; but if this fire ſhall not be ſtinted which now ſo troubleth thee, it will cauſe to thee that euer-endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fire more fierce and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable.</p>
            <p>Alſo,<note place="margin">The pleaſures of this life are momentanie, in reſpect of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them.</note> how long doeſt thou iudge the pleaſures of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life may endure? As I thinke thou canſt not liue 50. yeeres moe, admit thy old age be long. But in the meane while ſee what thinges befall, firſt in this behalfe, that no body is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine he may liue till night; next, for that the condition of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:26204:28"/> affaires is ſtill moueable, for many times life continueth many yeeres, but wealth and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches faile, and often ſome make ſhipwracke of goods before they die. But grant we, that thou maiſt both liue a long time, and ſuffer no alteration of times; yet what is this ſpace to euerlaſting paines; what is this voluptie to thoſe miſerable and vntollerable plagues? For in this life whether it be good or euill, it hath his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, &amp; that ſpeedily, but in the world to come both are euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Ouer and beſides, the ſtate of the very puniſhment is different: for the fire in this life co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumeth al things it taketh, but that fire whom it once taketh hold on, it vexeth &amp; alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth to the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it termed vnquenchable, not only bicaus it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it ſelfe, but bicauſe it doth not quench or ſley the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it taketh. For the ſcripture ſaith, that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners put on immortalitie, to wit,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:26204:28"/> profitable, not to honor of life, but to perpetuitie of correction.</p>
            <p>Now the force of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that puniſhment of that fire which is ſo forcible, no voice will ſerue to declare, no ſpeech will ſerue to vtter: for in good or euill things ſubiect to corruption, there is nothing like them.<note place="margin">The torments of hell ſet forth in their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</note> Neuertheleſſe that we may conceiue ſome motion of that fire and torment, call to minde, in him that hath a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ague, what tribulation, what anxietie of bodie and ſoule ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on each ſide, and by this temporall maladie gather what thoſe torments be which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with an eternall fire, which are watered before that horrible iudgement ſeat with a fierie ſtreame of tormenting waues. There what ſhall we do? What ſhal we anſwere? Nothing ſhall be there but gnaſhing of teeth, but ſcritching and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and too to late repentance, no way any helpe being founde,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26204:29"/> and euery way the torments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing without any comfort. We ſhal ſee none but the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners and tortours dreadfull to be beholden, and (which is woorſt of all) we ſhall haue no ſolace of the very aire. For vtter darknes ſhall compas the place of torments, and the fire which as it hath not a nature of conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ſo hath it not of illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but it is a darke fire, the flame thereof giuing no light. So that to them that are in it, what feare, what renting of their bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, what diſmembring of their bodies, what croſſes there be to euery ſenſe, no toong can tell. And as the ſortes of torments do varie and differ, ſo proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably euerichone to his ſinnes hath his paine multiplied.</p>
            <p>Now if thou ſhouldeſt ſay, how can the bodie continue in ſo wretched &amp; ſuch an endles tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting? Conſider what things now and then in this life betide vs, and by theſe ſmal things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26204:29"/> great. How that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we ſee ſome troubled with long ſicknes, and yet their life to indure: and howbeit the bodie be diſſolued by ſome death, yet the ſoule is not diſſolued nor conſumed: whence it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that when the body ſhal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo become immortall, no death may kill the ſoule or body. For in this preſent life it cannot be, that the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body ſhould be both grieuous &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, but the one yeeldeth to the other, for that the body can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide both. But when each ſhall put off corruption, the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption afore receiued ſhal end, but the incorruption gotten ſhal be endleſſe. So let vs not thinke, the very exceeding greatnes of puniſhment will cauſe an end of dolor, but (as I ſaid) our ſins ſhall aggrauate the chaſtiſement, and the incorruption of the bodie or ſoule ſhall not limite it.</p>
            <p>Tell me nowe, what ſpace of ſenſualitie and dainties wilt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:26204:30"/> thou liken to theſe tormentes? Let vs (if we liſt) beſtow on de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights an hundreth yeeres, adde thereto an hundreth moe, and tenne times an hundreth, what benefite will there bee gotten of it, if we conſider this euer-remaining paine? May not the whole time of this life, wherein we ſeeme to take pleaſure in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes, and wallow in wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, be rekoned as the dreame of one night, in compariſon of that eternitie? Is there any ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who to haue a delightſome dreame one night, would vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſempiternall pains? Or take that for this, or this for that?</p>
            <p>I diſpraiſe not as yet delights, nor vnfolde the bitternes of them, bicauſe the time ſerueth not for ſuch ſpeeches nowe, but then I ſhal be occaſioned when I ſee thee able to auoid the ſame. For, bicauſe thou art addicted to them, thou maiſt gheſſe we doa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if we auouch that pleaſure, which all men reckon accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26204:30"/> and gladſome, were yrke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſowre. But if by the mercie of God, thou maieſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape out of this ſort of ſicknes, at that time, yea at that time thou ſhalt finde out, what bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, yea what bane ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie hath. Now meane while let vs imagine, that paſtimes and pleaſure and voluptuouſnes are honeſt and comely: What ſhall we ſay to the puniſhments laide vp in ſtore for them? What ſhall we ſay to them, bicauſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights vade like a ſhadowe, and haſtily flie away, but the paine abideth for euer and euer?</p>
            <p>Grant the time and ſpace of paſtime and puniſhment were al one, is there any ſo fooliſh, or ſo depriued of his fiue wits, that would chuſe to tolerate one day of paine for a daye of pleaſure? ſith the pangs of one houre, and euerye vexation of the bodye, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly cauſeth vs to forget all the time paſt conſumed in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight. Wherfore for aſmuch as we
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:26204:31"/> may be rid (if in a moment we be turned) from euery of thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting chaſtiſements, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy eternall goodnes, why defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we? why ſtay we? why do we no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vſe the bountifulnes of God? Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this is prouided by the vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and infinite clemencie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, that labor and toile ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not be ſtretched far, nor be lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or endles, but ſhort, and (as may ſaye) for a minute of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houre. Such is this preſent life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it be conferred with that euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. The clemencie (I ſay) o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God hath prouided,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> that in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fleeting &amp; ſhort life, the ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be labors and agonies, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the life eternall, there ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be crownes and rewards of goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> workes, and that trauell ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoone be ended, but the reward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of good deedes ſhould laſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. And euen as this maket<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them glad that through ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring of toile indure a crowne: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it ſhall grieue and trouble thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the time to come, that ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:26204:31"/> they haue loſte (for a little and ſmall time of delights) perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good things, and haue ſought for ſtill induring euill things.</p>
            <p>Let vs not therefore incurre this anguiſh of ſoule, let vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake while we haue time. And lo now is the acceptable time, now is the day of ſaluation, now is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of repentance, and a time wherein repentance will not be fruitles. But if we be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of our life, we ſhall ſuſtaine in hell not theſe calamities alone, whereof we haue ſpoken, but a more grieuous miſchiefe. For to be excluded from bliſſe, and to be debarred from the things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Saintes, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch affliction, ſuch woful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as (if no outward puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment tormented) it were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. It ſurpaſſeth all paines of hell, to want that beatitude, the fruition of which lay in thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. For muſe (I deſire you) on the ſtate of that life,<note place="margin">Heauenly bliſſe ſet forth.</note> aſmuch as a man may conſider it, for as it is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26204:32"/> in deed, no ſpeech can vtter. Yet let vs comprehende an image thereof, to the vtmoſt it may be, by that we haue read, and the darke ſpeeches we haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. It is ſaid of it in a certaine place,<note place="margin">Reu. 21, 4. Iſai. 35.</note> There ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrowe, neither crying, neither ſhall there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more paine. What more feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie is there than this life, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no feare of pouertie, nor ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hurteth, none dealeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly, none is indangered, none conceiueth indignation, none enuieth, no deſire inflameth, no luſt of meat, no greedines of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and renowne troubleth: but euery ſpot of vice is blotted out &amp; waſhed away, where all things are in peace and ioyouſnes, all things in quiet and reſt, where is light and brightnes, not ſuch as is among vs, but by ſo much more cleare and glittering, by howe much more bright the ſun is nowe than any candle? There is no night, no darkenes, no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26204:32"/> of cloudes, no extremitie of cold or heate; but ſuch a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature ſhall there be of all things, as they alone ſhall knowe which are worthie to inioye the ſame. There is not olde age, nor the miſerie thereof, but euery corruptible thing is done away, and the glorie of incorruption is euery where. But moreouer to haue ſocietie with the Angels &amp; Archangels, and of all the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall and ſupernall powers to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the companie, is much to be eſteemed: but to obteine the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant ſight of our Lorde Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; to be lightned with the brightnes of his maieſtie, that can not be deſcribed, paſſeth all ſuch and ſuch like honor.</p>
            <p>But leſt thou be daunted with theſe things on the ſodaine, I will allure thee by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the attainement of them. Behold now and looke vpon the heauen, let thy thought alſo pierce a little aboue heauen, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ponder the transforming of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26204:33"/> the whole creature. For it ſhall not abide in this quality where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is, but it ſhalbe chaunged into another much more fine and faire, as much (let me ſay ſo) as gold exceedeth lead. Saint Paul teacheth this ſhall come to paſſe, when he ſaith, that the creature it ſelfe ſhalbe freed from the bondage of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Rom. 8, 21.</note> For now vnder corruption it ſuffereth many thinges which corruptible bodies muſt needs ſuffer: but when it ſhall caſt off all frailetie and corruption, it ſhalbe adorned with wonderfull bewtie, for it ſhall not ſuffer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible bodies, but it ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them (by reſurrection) void of corruption, whereby the very creature ſhalbe metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſed into an excellenter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite. There ſhalbe then no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention any where, but all things ſhall agree in amitie, for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the Saints ſhalbe one, there ſhalbe no dread of the Diuell, no ambuſhes of to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:26204:33"/> ſpirits, the feare of hell ſhalbe far off, there ſhalbe death neither of the body, nor of the ſoule, but feare by the meanes of immortalitie ſhalbe ſhaken off.</p>
            <p>Like as a kings ſonne if firſt of all he be foſtered vp in a poore cottage being apparailed in baſe raiment, liueth vnder the feare of Tutors, and gouernance of Maſters, whereby his yong age vnder ſtreite diſcipline may bring his mans-eſtate into good liking, and make it worthy his famous progenitors; but when the time commeth, that he muſt both enter the Court of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and take in hand his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſcepter, all homely appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raile being reiected, he arayeth himſelf in princely attire, &amp; on a ſuddain putteth on the mitre of his father, the glittering of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple incontinently is added, the brightnes of his diademe, the rowte of his gard, the power of his name is increaſed, and he is made a new man; ſo after ſuch a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:26204:34"/> manner ſhall the alteration of Saints be.</p>
            <p>And to the end you may be giuen to vnderſtand, that pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted words is not all we ſpeake, let vs caſt our eies on that mountaine wherein Chriſt was transformed, and let vs behold his brightneſſe, that, wherein (when he was transformed) he ſhined; neither for all that by this meanes, all the glory of the world to come ſhalbe reuealed vnto vs. For that transformation was declared not fully as in deed the bleſſednes to come ſhalbe, but aſmuch as the beholders eies could beare. And the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ſaith<note place="margin">Matt. 17, 2.</note> his face did ſhine as the ſunne: but the glory of the incorruptible ſhall not only ſend foorth ſuch a light, nor ſuch as the eies of men can look on, but ſuch ſhall be the future bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as eie ſight may not indure, although it abode that in the transforming on the mount. Wherby it is cleere, that ſo much
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:26204:34"/> was reuealed as the eies of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men could ſuffer, neither yet did they fully ſuffer it, for it is ſaid, They fell on their faces.<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, if thou ſhouldeſt be brought into an aſſemblie, where euery one ſhould ſit apparrelled in golden robes, in the middeſt of whome one ſhould ſhine dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in pearles and purple, and if he promiſed that thou mighteſt be one of the number of thoſe men of honor, wouldeſt thou not aſſay and attempt all thinges to attaine vnto it? So then open thy ſight on the heauens, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold there an aſſembly gathered togither, not in brightnes of gold, neither in trimnes of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor gliſtering in pretious ſtones, but clearer in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes than either the ſtars glitter, or the ſun ſhineth. Behold there a companie not of men alone, but of Aungels, Archaungels, thrones, dominions, principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and powers; and of the king that ſitteth in the middeſt of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26204:35"/> them, no ſpeech may be, for he ſurmounteth all ſpeech and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite of the mind of man, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his beautie, his ſtrength, his glory, his roialty, his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. What then? Tell me, ſhall we beguile our ſelues of all theſe honors, bicauſe of ſloth in ſuſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome labor, and in reſiſting for a while the allurements of luſt? For if we ſhould dailie ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine torments, and ſuffer a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time hell fire, to the ende we might ſee Chriſt comming in glory, and accompanied with his Saints, were it not good to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all ſorrowe, that we might be made partakers of ſo great bliſſe, of ſo great glory? Heare what the bleſſed Apoſtle Peter ſaith;<note place="margin">Matt. 17, 4.</note> It is good for vs to be here. If he ſeeing a ſlender glimſe of the glory to come, ſodainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected all things out of his mind, relieng on the delectation of the viſion he ſaw, what will one ſaie, if he beheld the things, as they are in truth? Namely at what
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:26204:35"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime, the court of heauen ſhal be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pened, and the king of heauen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall be reuealed, not in a glaſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arkly, but face to face, not by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith, but by viſage.</p>
            <p>Many ignorant folke thinke it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing al-ſufficient, and to be wiſhed for, alone to be deliuered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom the paines of hell; I ſay,<note place="margin">The torments of hell not ſo greeuous as the loſſe of the ſight of Christ.</note> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e remooued and caſt off from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat glorie, is a more grieuous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orment than hel: neither iudge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the torments there ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, as it is to be driuen from the ſight of Chriſt, for this (I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure you) is more miſerable than any puniſhment, this onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth hell. When wee ſee an earthly king entring his pallace, with his adherents and garde, we admire and call thoſe great men who waite vpon him, and ſuppoſe our ſelues wretched, if we be not vouchſafed any place amongeſt them: though wee knowe the weaknes and inſtabilitie of theſe terrene things, ſomtimes for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine warres, ſometimes for ciuil
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:26204:36"/> conterwaites, and ſometime for malitious ſpite, yet howſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer it be, it grieueth thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue fallen thence. Howe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall it not much more vexe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if with the higheſt king,<note place="margin">Iſai. 40.</note> who ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the whol globe of the eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (not a part thereof onely) ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who holdeth it in his fiſt, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meaſureth the heauen with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hand-breadth, who ſupporte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> each thing by the woorde of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power, who reckneth the Gentil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as nothing, yea as ſpettle, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this (I ſay) when he beſtoweth honor that ſhall laſt for euer, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue no place, neither be num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred amonge his ſeruants? Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it not pinche vs more than any paine?</p>
            <p>But peraduenture thou ſaieſt it will ſuffice vs to eſcape hell, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit we be not thought worthi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſight of the king. Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more vnhappie and wretche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule is there, than to which thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſufficient? Suppoſeſt thou tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the king whereof we ſpeake, ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:26204:36"/> come to iudge the earth, caried in chariots of Mules, or in gilded waggons, or with the terrible power of a diademe? Nay har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how the Prophets haue fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told (as much as might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to men) the comming of Chriſt. One of them ſaith thus: Our God ſhall come,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50, 3.</note> and ſhall not keepe ſilence, a fire ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure before him, and a mightie tempeſt ſhall be mooued round about him, he ſhall call the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue, &amp; the earth to iudge his people. And harken how ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to wit, Iſaiah, ſheweth the diuerſe ſortes of puniſhments; theſe are his words;<note place="margin">Iſai. 13, 9.</note> Beholde the day of the Lord commeth, cruel, with wrath, and fierce anger, to lay the land waſte; and he ſhall deſtroy the ſinners out of it.<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> For the ſtarres of heauen, and the planets thereof, ſhall not giue their light, the ſunne ſhal be dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened in his going foorth, and the moone ſhall not cauſe her light to ſhine.<note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> And I will viſit the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26204:37"/> wickednes vpon the world, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their iniquitie vpon the wicked and I wil cauſe the arrogancie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the proud to ceaſe.<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> I will make a man more precious than fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> golde, euen a man aboue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wedge of golde of Ophir. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I will ſhake the heauen,<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the earth ſhall remooue out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hir place, in the wrath of the Lord of hoſts, &amp; in the day of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fierce anger. And again he ſaith, the windowes from on high are open,<note place="margin">Iſa. 24, 18.</note> and the foundations of the earth do ſhake.<note place="margin">19.</note> The earth is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly broken downe, the earth is cleane diſſolued, the earth is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly mooued.<note place="margin">20.</note> The earth ſhall reele too &amp; fro like a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken man, &amp; ſhal be remoued like a tent, the iniquitie thereof ſhall be heauy vpon it, ſo that it ſhall fal and riſe no more. And in that day,<note place="margin">21.</note> ſhall the Lord viſit the hoa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> aboue, that is on high, euen the kings of the world, that are vpon the earth, and they ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered togither as the priſoners
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:26204:37"/> in the pit, and they ſhall be ſhut vp in the priſon. And the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Malachies words are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant hereto;<note place="margin">Malac. 3.</note> Behold he ſhall come, ſaith the Lorde of hoſtes.<note place="margin">Verſ. 1.2.</note> But who may abide the day of his comming? and who ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure when he appeereth? For he is like a purging fire, and like ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſope.<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> And he ſhall ſit downe to fine and try the ſiluer, he ſhall euen fine the ſonnes of Leuie, &amp; purifie them as golde and ſiluer. And againe he ſaith,<note place="margin">Chap. 4, 1.</note> for beholde the day commeth that ſhall burne as an ouen, and all the proude, yea, and all that do wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly ſhall be as ſtubble, and the day that commeth ſhall burne them vp, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, and ſhall leaue them neither roote nor branch. And another of the prophets ſaith,<note place="margin">Dan. 7, 9.</note> I behelde till the thrones were ſet vp, and the auncient of daies did ſit, whoſe garment was white as ſnow, and the haire of his head like the pure wooll.<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> A fierie
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26204:38"/> ſtreame iſſued, and came foorth from before him, the iudgement was ſet, and the bookes opened. And a little after,<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> as I beheld in viſions by night, behold one like the ſonne of man came in the cloudes of heauen, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto the ancient of daies, and they brought him before him.<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> And he gaue him domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and honor, and a kingdome, that all people, nations and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages ſhould ſerue him, his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion is an euerlaſting domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which ſhall neuer be taken away, and his kingdome ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be deſtroied.<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> I Daniel was troubled in my ſpirite, in the midſt of my body, and the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mine head made me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide.</p>
            <p>So then when theſe things ſhall begin, the gates of heauen ſhall be opened, yea rather the very heauen ſhal be taken away, as if the couerings of a pauilion were drawen togither, to wit, that it may be reſtored &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:26204:38"/> into better. Then all things ſhall be in feare, amazed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and trembling ſhall fill eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place. Then alſo feare ſhall ſhake the angels, and not the angels alone, but perchance the archangels, thrones, dominions, rules and powers. For this is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified where it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Iſai. 13, 13.</note> I wil ſhake the heauen; for they are the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſeruants of them that muſt be iudged, and muſt giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this life. If when one ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is to be iudged by the iudges of this worlde, other feare and ſhake, although it be not for great danger like to inſue: when the vniuerſall world ſhall come to be iudged of him that lacketh not witnes, that doth not ſeeke arguments, that doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire an orator for the cauſe, but all theſe things being remooued that doth reueale the deedes, wordes, and thoughts of men, that placeth ech thing in open ſight, and ſheweth euery fact, as it were in a painted table, before
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:26204:39"/> the eies, both of the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and of the beholders, how much more ſhall euery creature be mooued with feare? And if then no fierie ſtreame ſhould iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue foorth, neither the terrible angels, or greeſely executioners ſhould ſtand by; but if thus one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it were, that men ſhoulde be called before the king, and ſome ſhould be praiſed and honored, other ſome without honor caſt to confuſion; if men did onely ſuffer this puniſhment, would it not ſurpaſſe the torments of hel, that when other were endowed with gifts of the king, they ſhuld ſhamefully ſuffer the repulſe? Which paine how vntolerable it is, although ſpeech now may not declare, yet then ſhall we cleerely perceiue it, when we come to experience.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, beſides al theſe anguiſhes of torments, ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eies, not confuſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and vtter ſhame, but the way, how men are drawne to fire,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:26204:39"/> and deliuered vp to racking. Thinke vpon thoſe cruell &amp; oug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tortours, which throw ſinners downe headlond, and in that time, in which other that haue done well, by the bright &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Angels being carried before the high throne of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting King, ſhalbe rewarded with immortall gifts.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are accidents to that day, iudgement, and time, but that which enſueth, what toong can tell? What pelaſure, what ioy ſhall it be, to be with Chriſt, when the ſoule comming to hir proper vigor, ſhall with confidence begin to looke on God? none can declare the greatnes of that ioie. For ſhe triumpheth not alone for the fruition of the thinges preſent, but ſhe reioiceth much more bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe knoweth, there ſhalbe no end of her bleſſednes. And howbeit no ſpeech can ſet forth that gladnes and mirth, nor any thought conteine it, yet ſeeing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:26204:40"/> (as it were) a certaine ſhadowe of the thing to come, we will alſo endeuor to acquaint you with it, Demand we of the rich and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of this world, who vaunt in honors and power, with what gladnes they are puffed out? With how great delectation and pleaſure they are in loue with theſe things, ſo that ſometime they carry their noſes very high in the winde? And that, though they themſelues knowe, that theſe thinges are neither right happie, nor yet euerlaſting, but vaniſhe awaye ſooner than a dreame: which if they indure while this life remaineth, if we make the moſte of them wee can, they can indure no longer. Wherefore if men are ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ioious, for fraile and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie thinges: with what ioye ſhall we thinke thoſe ſoules to be filled, which haue gotten hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly &amp; eternall bliſſe? In which both quantitie and qualitie dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth ſo much from the other in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:26204:40"/> excellencie, (for all that in this life we account them good,) ſo that,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. 64, 4. 1. Cor. 2, 9.</note> neither eie hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor hart as yet hath vnderſtoode them. For as a little one is in the bellie of his mother; ſo are we in the worlde inwrapped ſtreitly in darknes, &amp; can not beholde the light and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the world to come. But when the time ſhall come,<note place="margin">Such corne at we ſowe heere, ſuch bread ſhal we eate in the world to come.</note> that this worlde ſhall trauell in birth with vs, and ſhal bring foorth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the brightnes of the future world all it hath conceiued, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall be found (by the meanes of ſinne) putrified or not of full growth, they goe from darkenes to darkenes, from tribulation to more bitter tribulation. But they that ſhall be perfect and like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the king, ſhe profereth to the father, as a worthie iſſue, to be placed in the miniſterie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and in the ſeates of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changels.</p>
            <p>Therefore will you goe that waie (my friend) that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:26204:41"/> and kingly bewty of thy ſoule may be polluted, and this world at the laſt reiect thee, but repaire quickly the image of thy father, repaire thy virtue, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and gallantnes, that amonge other thou maieſt be knowne of thy father.<note place="margin">The ſoule must be polliſhed more than the bodie, and God hath thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</note> The beautie of the bodie God hath limited with certaine naturall bonds, but the beautie of the ſoule hee hath made free, and ſubiect to no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, which leaueth farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the comlines of the bodie. Inſomuch that the trimnes of our ſoule is at the becke of God, yet in our power. For if the Lord had granted vs licence to vſe our owne fancie in our bodilie bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, wee ſhoulde haue beene burdened with ſuperfluous and nought auaileable cares, ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the time of our life in them, whereby the ſoule muſt needes not be decked. Sith euen now, when we haue no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the trimnes of our bodies, we ſo carke and care, that by all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:26204:41"/> meanes we polliſh them, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying by the painting of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, by the friſling of our hairs, by the roaling of our eies, by va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of veſtiments, by exquiſite practiſes to augment our bodilie brauerie. But how much more conuenient were it for vs, to goe about to garniſh the ſoule, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the true beauty is, and ſuch as may by vs dailie be made more beautifull? Yet we on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, conſume the whole race of our life in ſpoiling the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, &amp; in adorning the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: leauing the miſtreſſe (like a vile bonde woman) vntrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, beſpotted, vtterly couered with all vnſeemely ſluttiſhnes. When as God for this cauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted vs from the carke of this bodie, and incloſed it within the bonds of nature, leaſt being oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in needeles cares, we ſhoulde neglect the beautifieng of our ſoule,<note place="margin">Soules defiled with ſin, may be trimmed a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaine.</note> whoſe beautie and brauenes, albeit it be brought to extreme pollution, yet by our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:26204:42"/> and diligence ſhe may be reſtored to notable gaineſſe, and be recouered ſo farre, that ſhe may not onely be admired of all good men, but be deſired and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the king himſelfe, who is Lord of all. As the Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to it in the Pſalmes:<note place="margin">Pſal. 45, 11.</note> The king ſhall haue pleaſure in thy beautie.</p>
            <p>Often times experience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, that of thoſe women which haue beene inured to common brothelrie, if any be ſomewhat handſome, for fairenes ſake ſhe hath beene vnited in matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to ſome good man, and hath beene drawne to honeſtie. How much rather will not God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne ne deſpiſe the ſoules, which haue fallen from their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine excellency by the tyrannie of the diuell, into the brothel-houſe and ſtewes of this preſent life? You ſhall find that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue vſed theſe examples when they ſpake to Hieruſalem, for ſhe plaied the diſhoneſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:26204:42"/> and went a whooring after a ſtrang ſort, as ſheweth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ezechiel, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ezech. 16, 33.</note> they giue gifts to all other whoores, but thou giueſt gifts vnto thy louers,<note n="*" place="margin">Verſ. 34.</note> and the contrary is in thee from other women. And againe another ſaith, thou haſt ſitten vpon the way waiting for them, as a deſolate<note n="*" place="margin">G. quaile. Or, thou hast ſit waiting for them in the waies, as the Arabian in the wildernes. <hi>Hier. 3, 2.</hi>
               </note> Chough. This peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which had ſo plaied the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot the Lord reclaimed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for their captiuitie was not ſo much for their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as for their amendment. For if in caſe GOD woulde haue puniſhed and deſtroied them withall, he would not haue brought them home againe to their natiue ſoile, neither would haue cauſed them to reedifie with greater magnificency, their citie and temple which were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen,<note place="margin">Hagg. 2, 10.</note> the glory (ſaith he) of this laſt houſe, ſhall be greater than the firſt. So then if God do not forbid repentance to thoſe that haue ſo manifoldly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:26204:43"/> whoordome, he will much more willingly reclaime thy ſoule, which now firſt hath grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly falne.<note place="margin">God is iealous ouer our ſouls.</note> The reaſon is, for that no carnall louer, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo hoate, can be ſo iealous ouer the loue of his derling, as God is kindled with the loue of our ſoules. Which albeit daily it may be gathered, yet it may be apparantly proued out of the word of God. In a word, read that is ſpoken of God, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning either of Ieremie, or of the other Prophets, howe when he was deſpiſed and ſet light by of the people, yet he returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to them, and thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their loue, he continually fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them. And this is that, which God himſelfe declareth in the Goſpell, where he ſaith: Hieruſalem,<note place="margin">Mat. 23, 37. Luk. 13, 34.</note> Hieruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which are ſent to thee, howe often would I haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thy children togither, as the Hen gathereth hir chickens, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:26204:43"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e would not. And Paule ſaith to the Corinthians:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2, 19.</note> For God was in Chriſt, and reconciled the world to himſelfe, not imputing their ſinnes vnto them, &amp; hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to vs the word of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. Now then are we Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors for Chriſt:<note place="margin">20.</note> as though God did beſeeche you through vs, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead, that yee bee reconciled to God. Let vs thinke theſe things ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to vs, for not onely infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but the pollution &amp; vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life maketh this execrable enimitie betwixt God and men, and ſo the Apoſtle ſaieth, that<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8, 7.</note> the wiſedome of the fleſh is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie againſt God. Go to then, let vs raze to the ground this wal of enimitie, let vs ſmooth the way to an attoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with God, that we may be loued and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of him againe.</p>
            <p>I am ſure you woonder not a little at the beautie of Hermio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,<note place="margin">Hermione daughter to Menelaus and Helena very beautifull for whom Orestes the ſonne of Agamemnon ſlew Pyrrhus the ſonne of Achilles, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed minion.</note> and thinke the like may not be founde on the whole earth.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:26204:44"/> But if you would (my friend) yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be ſo much fairer and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lier than ſhe, by how much gold exceedeth dirte. For if many haue in admiration the beautie of that body, and fall in loue therewith; what fairenes do you thinke to be in a ſoule, if euerie point therein were liuely por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traited? How much more amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how much more woonderful would it be? For the ſubſtance of bodilie beautie conſiſteth in naught elſe, but in phlegme, blood, moiſture, and<note n="*" place="margin">Or, melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly.</note> gal, which are maintained by the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iuyces of meats? Hereby the apples of the eies gliſter, hereby the cheekes are ruddie, &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the whole face is adourned. And vnles they be daily moiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſuch iuice, which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth out of the liuer, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent the skin is dried vp, the eies wax hollow, al ruddines and beautie departeth from the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. Now if thou conſider what is hidden within that skin which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26204:44"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ou iudgeſt beautifull, what is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut vp within the noſethriles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat within the iawes and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, thou wilt proteſt that this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rauery of body, is nothing but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>anched ſepulchre, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut appeereth faire to men, but within is full of filthines and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes. Moreouer, if thou ſee on a ragged cloath, the phlegme and ſpittle that proceedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, thou loatheſt it, &amp; wilt not touch it with the tip of the finger, looking askew thereon: and how then canſt thou loue &amp; deſire the cel &amp; ſeat of phlegme? But thy beauty was not ſuch. For by how much heauen is more beautifull than the earth, by ſo much did the trimnes of thy ſoule ſurmount the beautie of the faireſt body. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding none at any time hath ſeene a ſoule departed from the body, yet ſome other time I will attempt to declare the comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it, by the powers thereof. At this time let it ſuffice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:26204:45"/> the words of the Lorde which ſay,<note place="margin">Matt. 22, 30. Mark. 12, 25.</note> they are as the ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God in heauen. Again, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of bodies there is ſo great a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, betweene thoſe that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thin, and thoſe that are thick and heauy, (as for example hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen paſſeth the earth, fire water the ſtars ſtones, the rain-bow al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> terreſtriall flowers:) what woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſay, if it might ſo chance, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with corporall eies, we might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the gaines of the ſoule. Wouldeſt thou not ſcoffe at all externall beauty and brauery, in conſideration of that internal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſubſtance? I pray thee then let vs not contemne ſo great a feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, nor not lightly regarde ſo great a treaſure that is in vs, eſpecially ſith a returne is not hard, and with no great labour may all the beautie of our ſoule be renued. For aſſoone as thou ſhalt imagine the thinges to come, and ſhalt be inamered with them, ſtraightway the ſoule retireth to hir former brauenes.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:26204:45"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o it is written; For our light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4, 17.</note> which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, cauſeth vnto vs a far more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xcellent, and an eternal weight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f glory.<note place="margin">18.</note> While we looke not on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he things which are ſeene, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the things which are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eene, for the things which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een are corporal, but the things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich are not ſeene are eternal. Now if Paul call tribulations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght and eaſie, for that we looke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot on the thinges which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een, but on the things which are not ſeene: how much more eaſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall it be for thee, to ſhake off the ſoule burden of vncleannes? Neither nowe do I exhort thee to thoſe labours and dangers, or to thoſe daily deaths, which the Apoſtles ſuffred, or to thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, or ſtripes, or bands, or impriſonments, or the contempt of all worldly riches, or famine, or nakednes, or many watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or perils of iourneying, or ſhipwracks on ſea, or dangers of robbers, or dangers of thy owne
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:26204:46"/> nation, or dangers of falſe br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren, for al thoſe afflictions th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> apoſtles indured: nothing of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe I require of thee, but this deſire alone, that ſeruitude be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing forſaken, thou returne to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> former liberty, conſidering both the plague which followeth riot and the glory which is laide vp for vertues. It is no maruell, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe which beleeue there ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be no reſurrection, neglect thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life, feare nothing the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, and are nothing pricked in hart: but we which looke more certainely on future than preſent things, ought we to liue ſo miſerably, &amp; ſo wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we not onely ſhould not feare, at the remembrance of the iudgement to come, but vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly contemne it?</p>
            <p>A part it is of extreme mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and no miſchiefe is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that beleeuing we be like the vnbeleeuing. Yea amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not a few haue beene found, who haue floriſhed in this life, in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:26204:46"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he vertues of the mind, &amp; what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall be our excuſe, what our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace, if in the daie of doome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe ſhall be brought foorth for examples againſt vs? Some that exerciſe marchandice we ſee haue ſuffred ſhipwracke, &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſſe of all their goods: yet for this they haue not beene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied, but againe haue applied the ſame way and traffike. Theſe did leeſe their ſubſtance not by ſloth, but by violence of windes. But we which know afore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, that if we our ſelues will, we may incur neither ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, neither damage of ſoule; ſhould we not take in hand againe our former exerciſes, and renew our buſines by negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence ouerſlipped? Neuertheles we lie retchleſly, and fold our idle hands on our breaſt, after the manner of ſluggards: and would God our hands were idle, and did not worke our owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay. Which if they doo it hath great affinitie with moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:26204:47"/> outrage, as if (for example a champion leauing his aduerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, ſhould turne his hands on hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne head, and buffet himſelfe The diuell hath put vs to fligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and hath daſhed vs in ſunder, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue neede then to riſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to reſiſt him. When thou an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> once caſt downe, if thou be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling not onely to lie ſtill, but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> throw down thy ſelfe headlong this is to aſſent to thine eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and to take in defence hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed Dauid fell after the ſame ſort thou diddeſt, neither ſo alone, but in more greeuous wiſe, for he combined murder with adultery: and what did he then? Did hee lie ſo? Did hee not riſe and reſiſt the enimie, and ſo ouercame him, that his good deeds profited his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie when he was gone? For when Salomon had committed that hainous crime, and was deemed woorthy of a thouſand deathes, yet for Dauids ſake the Lorde
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:26204:47"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid he woulde beſtow the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome on him longer. Theſe be the wordes;<note place="margin">2. King. 11, 11</note> I will ſurely rent the kingdome from thee, and will giue it to thy ſeruaunt. Notwithſtanding in thy daies I will not do it,<note place="margin">12.</note> bicauſe of Dauid thy father, but I will rent it out of the hand of thy ſonne. Hezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah when he was much indange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, (albeit he were a iuſt man himſelfe,) yet for bleſſed Dauid the Lord promiſed to help him,<note n="*" place="margin">Or, J will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this citie to ſaue it for mine owne ſake, and for Dauid my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſake.</note> I will defend this citie for mine owne ſake,<note place="margin">2. King. 19, 34</note> and for Dauid my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſake, I will ſaue it. See what was the ſtrength of repentance, ſee what power conuerſion had. But if hee had thus thought, (which thou now thinkeſt,) and had ſaid, it is impoſſible that the Lord ſhoulde nowe be mercifull to me, he hath greatly honored me, and hath endued me with the gift of prophecie, he hath exalted me to a kingdome, he hath deliuered me from mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold dangers, how then can I
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:26204:48"/> promerite clemencie at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hands of God, foraſmuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue thus fallen? Yf Dauid ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thus thought, he had loſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely that went afore, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that followed alſo. For not only the wounds of the body if they be neglected bring death; but the wounds of the ſoule ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Are we ſo ſottiſh to put a plaiſter to a bodily wound, and neuer attempt to cure the ſoule Many woundes of our bodies may not be cured, yet we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire not, and though the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions ſay, the wound is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureable, yet we earneſtly and vrgently beſeech them, that they would mittigate ſomewhat the paine. But in the wounds of the ſoule, which are not vnſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (for the ſoule is not tied to neceſſitie, neither abideth any paſſion) we are remiſſe, we are paſt hope, we are pricked with no care. When there is no hope our griefe of body may be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, yet we withdraw nothing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:26204:48"/> from our care: but here when no occaſion is of deſperation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vſing any labor, we omite all care. So you perceiue, how that more ardently we loue our body than our ſoule, knowing not, that if we regard not our ſoule, we cannot ſaue our body. For the ſoule was not ordained for the body, but the body for the ſoule: and he that eſteemeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the higher, but poliſheth the inferiour, marreth both. But he that obſerueth an order, and garniſheth the firſt, admit he do not paſſe for the ſecond, by the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuertheles of the firſt, the ſecond ſhall be ſaued. The which is builded on the plot of Chriſt his words,<note place="margin">Matt. 10, 28.</note> Feare ye not them which kil the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare him, which is able to deſtroy both ſoule and bodie in Hell.</p>
            <p>Thinke you we haue done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and ſatisfied you in this thing, that no infirmitie of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:26204:49"/> ſoule is vncureable? Or elſe is it needefull we ſhould vſe other reaſons, and confirme it yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? For although a thouſand times thou deſpaire of thy ſelfe, we will neuer deſpaire of thee. Neither do we this that we miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in other, howbeit there be ods, whether one deſpaire of himſelfe, or another of him. To deſpaire of another is pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but to deſpaire of himſelfe, is not: bicauſe he is not maſter of anothers minde, this ruleth his owne purpoſe. Wherefore we hope there is a returne for you to the ſtate of your former life, and to the vertues of the mind, which we know are in you. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe things, this we adde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ion. 2, 4.</note>The Nineuites heard the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaying definitely, Yet four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie daies and Nineueh ſhall be ouerthrowen, notwithſtanding they were not diſcouraged. No not when they were not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the Lord would not bring to paſſe his words, &amp; when
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:26204:49"/> (in mans iudgement) there was no hope of forgiuenes. And aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as that abrupt ſaying was ended, they determined repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſaying,<note place="margin">Verſe. 9. 10.</note> who can tell if God will turne and repent, and turne away his fierce wrath that we periſh not. And God ſaw their workes that they turned from their euil waies: and God repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the euill that he had ſaid he would doo vnto them, and he did it not. If Barbarians and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant folke could vnderſtand ſo much of the mercy of God, doth it not much more behoue vs to do ſo, who are enſtructed in the word of God, &amp; know this example was before our time, and that many moe like are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Gods Booke, either in words, or in actes? For my thoughts are not your thoughts,<note place="margin">Iſai. 55, 8.</note> neither are your waies my waies, ſaith the Lord.<note place="margin">9.</note> For as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens are hier than the earth, ſo are my waies higher than your waies, and my thoughts aboue
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:26204:50"/> your thoughts.</p>
            <p>Futhermore if we receiue our ſeruants, who haue offended vs, when they promiſe they will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende, and account of them as afore, nay many times credit them more after reconcileme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; will not God much rather deale thus with vs? If he had made vs to puniſh vs, thou mighteſt well deſpaire, and doubt of thy ſaluation: but if for his goodnes onely he made vs, to enioy hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euer-enduring bliſſe &amp; rewards, and doth all things from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world til this day, to this end and purpoſe, that he may ſaue vs: what matter of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing, what matter of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubting is there left?</p>
            <p>Wee haue offended him (ſay you) more than euer any man. For this cauſe ſhouldeſt thou more ſpeedilie &amp; earneſtly make ſatisfaction, and be ſorrowful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for thine offence, &amp; abandon thoſe deedes with which God is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Neither doth a grieuous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:26204:50"/> offend any bodie ſo much, as to continue in it, when there is time and opportunitie of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. To ſinne is humane, but to perſeuer in ſinne, is diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. To conclude, beholde howe God by the Prophet miſliketh this more than that:<note place="margin">Hier. 3, 7.</note> And I haue ſaid (ſaith hee) after that ſhee hath in all this gone a whooring,<note n="*" place="margin">Or, and I ſaid, when ſhe had done all this, turne thou vnto me, but ſhe returned not.</note> be thou turned to me, and ſhe is not turned. And otherwhere, when he had rebuked the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the people, by his Prophet, and they had promiſed amendment, he ſheweth how lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly he receiueth the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinners, who will graunt their hart maye bee ſo in them, that they may feare me, &amp; keepe my commaundements all the daies of their life, that it may be well with them, and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for euermore? Moſes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when he would teache the people, what God requireth of men, ſaith thus: And now, Iſrael,<note place="margin">Deut. 10, 12.</note> what doth the Lord thy God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:26204:51"/> of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walke in all his waies, and to loue him, and to ſerue the Lord thy God with all thy hart, and with all thy ſoule?</p>
            <p>God then, who is deſirous that himſelfe be beloued of vs, and for this doeth all things, not ſparing his onely begotten for our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; the loue he bare towards vs, would faine (after what ſorte ſoeuer, if I may ſo ſpeake,) we ſhould be reconciled to him; and how can it be, that he ſhould not receiue and loue vs being peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents conuerted vnto him, and that as chearfully as he doth his children? For, in what reſpect do you thinke, ſpake he by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſaying: Tell thou thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities firſt, that thou maiſt be iuſtified?<note place="margin">Amantium irae amoris redintegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt.</note> Was it not, for that he coueted to reuoke vs to his loue, and tender affection? He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his friend, if perchaunce he ſuffer many iniuries at his hands, his loue is not for that cooled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his beloued, if in caſe he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:26204:51"/> will let the wrongs to be opened &amp; diſcouered, and certes he that is iniuried, doeth deſire this for no other cauſe, but that their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of loue may be of more force and validitie. Nowe, if the confeſſion of ſinnes mattreth ſo much to attonement, how much greater may be our hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, if by workes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, we blot out the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we haue committed? For if God prohibited the fallen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the right waie, either none, or very fewe, ſhould enter the kingdom of heauen. Yea, the chiefe Patriarchs whom we haue in admiration, after backeſlides in ſinnes, they haue bene reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For they that were earneſt in euill, being turned to goodnes, vſe the ſame forwardnes, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their debt is great. In the goſpel this is taught of the Lord, when he ſaid to Simon of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine woman,<note place="margin">Luk. 7, 44.</note> Seeſt thou this woman? I entered into thine houſe, and thou gaueſt me no
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:26204:52"/> water to my feete, but ſhe hath waſhed my feete with teares, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiped them with the haires o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her head.<note place="margin">45.</note> Thou gaueſt mee no kiſſe, but ſhe ſince the time I came in, hath not ceaſed to kiſſe my feete.<note place="margin">46.</note> My head with oile thou diddeſt not annoint: but ſhe hath annointed my feete with oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">47.</note> Wherfore I ſay vnto thee, many ſins are forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir, for ſhe loued much. To whom a little is forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he doth loue a litle. And he ſaid vnto hir,<note place="margin">48.</note> thy ſins are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen thee. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r which cauſe the diuell knowing that they which haue ſolde themſelues to worke iniquitie, if they reuolt are dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and ſerious, and as in their tranſgreſſions they were haſtie, ſo in their amendment they are heedful (bicauſe now they know what they haue done,) he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth &amp; ſhaketh leaſt any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould make the onſet to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. For if they once begin, they may not be withſtaied, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dled with the heate of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:26204:52"/> as it were with a fire, they make their ſoules purer than fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed golde, and by the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their former miſdeeds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd as it were by the blowing wind of their conſcience, hauing hope their pilote, they arriue in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he hauen of health. And bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the honours paſt, the circumſpecter they are in their iourney; ſo that in this wel-nigh they may ſeeme to paſſe thoſe that neuer faultered,<note place="margin">Experientia ſtultorum mater.</note> bicauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience maketh them more charie. For (I know not how) we loue more entirely the thinges we had and haue loſt, than the thinges we haue not and deſire to get.</p>
            <p>Then a hard thing it is (as I ſaide) to make a beginning, in this lieth all the difficultie, to prepare the way to repentance. For ſtraightway at the entrance the enimy bloweth out threates and manacings, and in his rage driueth vs back, when we would go foorth. The ſmokie puffes,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:26204:53"/> and cloude of whoſe terrours, if thou contemne, when the way is entered, thou ſhalt ſee thy ſelfe corroborated, and obteining the conqueſt thou wilt reioice thine enimie manaced thee, and thou ſhalt perceiue the reſt of this combate eaſie. Go to, go to in the name of God, now let vs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the path of life, let vs returne to the heauenly citie, ſeeing we are appointed and inrolled citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens. The gates of this citie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire ſhurteth againſt vs, hope and confidence will open them fully; the which if we caſt behind vs, we incurre the crime not of ſloath alone, but of arrogancie. For ſathan was made as he is, by no other means, but for that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ſinne, firſt he deſpaired, and next fell from deſpaire into hawtines and pride. So likewiſe the ſoule if it once begin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of ſaluation, it vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not into what miſchiefes it runneth, fearing not to ſpeake or do whatſoeuer may ſtop ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:26204:53"/> Commonly wee ſee in thoſe that are mad, when once they haue loſt their wit, they feare nought any longer, they bluſh at nothing, but licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they dare ſpeake and do eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing. If they fall into the fire, they auoid it not; if they be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a headlong place, they pull not backe their foote. After the ſame maner they that are in deſpaire commit intollerable actes, they range in al the waies of wickednes, ſhame is no let, feare hindereth nothing, the things preſent do not refraine them, the things to come do not terrifie, death onely it is that they cannot eſcape.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I humbly requeſt thee, before the poiſon of this ſinne more infect thee, ariſe and awake at the laſt, and lay aſide this diuelliſh droonkennes. If on the ſudden thou canſt not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy wits togither, yet do it leiſurely, although (in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) it be the eaſier way at once
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:26204:54"/> to breake off all the ſtaies of this euill, to ſheere it in ſunder fully, and to begin repentance anew. But if this be difficile vnto thee, as thou wilt and art able, begin a better conuerſation, and couet eternall life. Runne therefore I pray and beſeech you deare friend, (I beſeech you for thoſe good deeds you haue done here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, I pray you for the libertie that firſt you had,) let me ſee you climbe vp to the top of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as truely a repentant as you were before. Yeelde to me thy friend, yeeld to all them that are offended through thee, and fall bicauſe of thy fall, yeelde to all them that are in deſpair bicauſe of thy deſpaire, that they may not ſurmiſe they can not treade the true waie, vnles they ſee thee returne. Regarde (I deſire you) the penſiuenes of the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the faithfull bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the great ioie and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing of the faithles, the vſuall by word of ſlouthfull youthes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:26204:54"/> what authoritie thou art to manie to wallowe in the mire of riot. And if ſo be that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into the waie of your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vertues, all theſe things will be turned into the contrary. Our ſhame and confuſion ſhall light on them, we ſhall be ioifull and glad. For wee will blaze abroade throughout the world, that thou art a ſubduer of luſt, a ſubduer of vncleane and fooliſh voluptie &amp; riot, and we will brute farre and wide thy glorious triumph. That victory is the greater that is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten after a fall, and that is reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after flight. And you ſhall not only be rewarded for your owne labour and reformation, but ſhal receiue a meede for the ſafetie of them, who leuelling their life to thy conuerſation, haue (without deſpaire) be turned themſelues to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance. Neither any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after hauing fallen howſoeuer, will not be greedie by and by to riſe, and incontinentlie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. Deſpiſe not (if you loue
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:26204:55"/> me) theſe great profits, neither bring our ſoules with ſorrowe to the graue: but vouchſafe vs ſome reſt, and chaſe away the cloude of heauines, which for thy ſake hath ouercouered vs; for loe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting paſſe our owne euils, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile thy fall. But if you would a little looke vpward, &amp; be in loue with celeſtiall things, we ſhould be eaſed of this lamenting, and we might be cauſed to conſider our owne offences.</p>
            <p>That men may by repentance repaire their priſtine gaines, yea ſomtimes be made more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than before they were, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto we haue confirmed out of the worde of God. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point, this is the cauſe why that harlots and Publicans inherite the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and that manie that were laſt, ſhall be firſt. Hencefoorth I will adde the things that haue beene done in our age, of which<note n="*" place="margin">G. F. C. of which my ſelfe may be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> thou thy ſelfe art a witnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">G. F. C. I know.</note>You knowe that yoong man
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:26204:55"/> the ſonne of VRBANVS, the chiefeſt of that prouince, whoſe parents died in his minority, but left him verie wealthie in houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuffe, golde, ſiluer, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions. That youth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temning at the firſt all pompe, and pride, (which that age and riches for the moſt part follow) he left the ſchooles of humane artes, and betooke himſelfe to a baſe life, in which putting on courſe and homely arayment, he departed to the mountaines and deſart places. Where being exerciſed in the temperancie of true phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, he not onelie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched (which is but ſeldome ſeen in thoſe yeeres,) but paſſed to, great and woonderfull men in the vertue of abſtinencie; yea, when afterwarde he was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed he paſſingly increaſed in vertues. At which thing all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioiced, and praiſed the Lorde, that borne to ſo great wealth, &amp; deſcended of ſuch a family, euen in the April of his dais he trode
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:26204:56"/> vnderfoote at once all vanitie of this momentary life, and had an hungrie deſire of eternall ioye.</p>
            <p>Liuing after this ſort, and in this admiration, among all, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his kindred (but naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons) at the firſt came to ſee him,<note place="margin">Euill ſpeeches corrupt good maners.</note> and after by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of lewde talke, drewe him againe to that he hated and loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, ſo that all philoſophie (which he ſtudied) being laied apart, he came from the hils to the market place. Then caried on a palfrey through the midſt of the citie, &amp; garded with foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men he vauntingly began to wander vp and down the ſtreets. Inſomuch that the rains of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie were alſo let looſe, bicauſe it hath no fellowſhip with dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ryot. After this he was ſnarled in the baite of filthy loue, and led into captiuitie by euery luſt, which cauſed all men to deſpaire of his ſaluation. For ſwarmes of paraſites enuironed
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:26204:56"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his hope-loſt yonker, the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erous rabble compaſſed him in. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd what hope woulde a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hinke to be remaining? Thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo which were giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reprehending, founde fault <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith this likewiſe, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nning he entred a courſe, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not continue in, and had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpired to that was aboue his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>each, forſaking the ſtudie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earning wherein he might haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rofited.</p>
            <p>When theſe and ſuch like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings as touching his life being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umored abroad were knowne to all, and we alſo were aſhamed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his doing; certaine holy men, expert in this kinde of hunting, and who had found out by long vſe and experience, that naught was to be deſpaired, putting on the armour of hope, they began to watch him more narrowly. And if it fortuned he were in the ſtreat, they approched neere and courteouſly ſaluted him; but he on horſe-backe ſcarce
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:26204:57"/> greeted them againe, or thought them worthy an anſwere, when they went by his ſide; ſuch was his pride and wickednes. But thoſe mercifull men, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting none of theſe an iniurie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected onely that they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that they might (if it were poſſible by any meanes) deliuer the lambe out of the teeth of woolues; which by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience was in fine atchiued. For weighing they did this often, &amp; prying into his owne life with the inward eies of his minde, he bluſhed ſomewhat at their bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and tendring, and when he marked they came a far off, he would diſmount from his horſe, and bowing his head towardes the earth, he hearkened dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to their ſpeeches, and in proceſſe of time he reuerenced them more. And ſo reuolting by peece-meale, through the grace of God, and their meeke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and rid fromall the nets of death wherin he was intangled,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:26204:57"/> he went againe to the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to the mountaines, and to the woonted exerciſes of philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, and after was of ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, that his latter doings ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his woonderfull begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. He learned by proofe the occaſion of his fall, and the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurement of all his error. That alſo he did, which (doubtles) was agreeable to Chriſts commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in the Goſpell;<note place="margin">Matt. 19, 21.</note> Selling all he had, and diſtributing it on the poore, to the end he might remooue his treaſure from the earth to heauen, and his hart might be there, where his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was. But bicauſe as yet he had ſomewhat left on earth, his hart returned to the earth, and making an eſtimate of all his goods, (for he cared nothing for them,) he beſtowed much on the needy, that ſo freeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from care of minde, he might take away all occaſion of ſtumbling. And thus walking in the way to heauen, by amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:26204:58"/> he is come to ech accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of vertue. So you ſee, how this yoong man fell quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and aroſe ſpeedily.</p>
            <p>Another alſo after many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours he had ſuſteined in the wildernes, hauing onelie the company of one in his life and manſion-place, continued an Angelicall life, from his yoong age, to his verie old daies. But (I know not how) drowſily yeelding to the ſuggeſtion and firſt batterie of the diuel,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Good Lord, how much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is there betweene the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Maſſe-mongring Moonks now being, &amp; the Monks which were in Chryſoſtoms daies? Thoſe were continent, and ſequestred (although they ſhould haue had a care of the ſaluation of their brethren alſo) themſelues from the vulgar ſort of men, to the end they might giue themſelues wholy to contemplation and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, (for this was the cauſe why Baſill the great went to Pontus, and inuited his friend Gregorie the Diuine to him;) theſe are lecherous and lustfull, coueting that ſort of life for idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes alone, and belliecheere. Thoſe as ſoone as they perceiued their vncleannes (this fellowe heere alledged is a witnes) fel to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce without ſtay: theſe through ſenſualitie committing groſſe &amp; carnall ſins, neuer truly repent for it, and yet beare men in hand they are the holiest perſons vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſunne. Of whom it was ſaid rightly, though in a rithme,
<q>
                        <l>O monachi, veſtri ſtomachi,</l>
                        <l>ſunt amphora Bacchi!</l>
                        <l>Vos eſtis, Deus eſt teſtis, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſſima peſtis.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let none then of the ignoranter ſort ſuppoſe, that this example maketh ought for the vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Moonks now a daies.</p>
               </note> he fell into the deſire of a woman, when as he neuer ſaw any, ſithence he becam a Moonke. Firſt, then hee deſired his fellowe with whom he liued, to bring him wine, &amp; fleſh to feede on, who making no haſte, he threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:26204:58"/> him, that he would go down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the city. Which he ſaide not that he might eat fleſh, but that he might finde opportunity to ſatiſfie his luſt. His compaignion marueling at this, and fearing leaſt he ſhould do him more harme, if he ſhoulde denie his requeſt, gaue that hee asked, and fulfilled his will. When he ſawe no waie to guile, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſhameleſſely hee reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his deſire, and confeſſeth he will goe downe to the citie. The other by much perſwaſion not able to reteine him, let him goe, and followed him farre off, to ſee what he would doe, and whither he would goe. And when a great waie behind, he ſaw him entring a brothell-houſe, &amp; to haue coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his luſt with the companie
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:26204:59"/> of a ſtrumpet, tarieng at the dore, ſtraightway when he came foorth, hee exhorted him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, he imbraced him, and louingly kiſſed him, and rebuked him not for his fall, but deſired him, that now his luſt being coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, he would returne to his olde habitation, and to the ſolitarie wildernes. But he marking in him ſuch meekenes and gentlenes, was aſhamed, &amp; ſtriken through with the force of his wordes and deedes, and condemning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for his miſdemeanor, goeth with his fellowe (which was ſo good &amp; humble) into the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. Whither when they came, he intreated of him, that when he was ſhut vp cloſely in his cell, and heremitage, he would<note n="*" place="margin">G. F. C. daily.</note> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſecond daie bring him bread and water. If anie ſhould ſeeke him, he willed him ſaye, that he was<note n="*" place="margin">G. F. C. aſleep.</note> dead. Which things obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he ſhut himſelfe in, &amp; there abode, clenſing the foulenes of his ſinne, with faſting, praiers,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:26204:59"/> and weeping.</p>
            <p>Few daies paſſed ouer, when a drowth (bicauſe of the want of raine) had hurted the countrie neere about him, and all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that land lamented much. But one of them was war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a dreame to goe to that man incloſed in a cell, that he might pray, and that by no other waie raine might bee procured, but by his praiers. So departing with ſome other taken to him, he found this Monkes complice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and demaunded where he was, whome the viſion admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed him to ſeek. When he heard he was dead, he deemed his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on falſe, and they returned all to praier, but the ſame viſion tolde him againe the ſame thinges. Whereat earneſtlye intreating him, that before had deceiued them, they requeſted him to ſhewe them the man, affirming that by the authoritie of ſo mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous a viſion, they were ſent to him being aliue, not dead. Seing
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:26204:60"/> it was the will of God, he brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth them to that godlie man, and the wall being broken down (becauſe he had ſhut the doore) they enter in and fall before hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> feete, deſiring him (when the trueth of the matter was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) to releaſe the famine by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion. Firſt, his excuſe was, that he coulde not demerite ſo great a thing: at which wordes, he burſt foorth into weeping for the offence he had committed, as if he had ſeene it freſh before his eies. At length for the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of the requeſters, (for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as hee perceiued GOD would haue it ſo,) he gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſupplication, and out of hand there followed great ſtore of rain, wherwith both the earth and men were refreſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Read Euſebius hist. eccl. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>What ſhould I ſpeake of him which firſt was the Diſciple of Iohn the<note n="*" place="margin">G. F. C. ſonne of Zebedeus.</note> Apoſtle, but after practiſed robbing for a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time? Neuertheles afterward, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle gat holde on him, as hee
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:26204:60"/> came out from the robbers den, and brought him againe (as you well knowe) to his former life, ſo that his beginning was not to be conferred with his end. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber when you read this ſtorie, you admired the incredible meeknes of this bleſſed Apoſtle, and among other tokens of his ſincere loue towards him, which he ſhewed, this you ſaid you moſt wondered at, that he kiſſed the hand of the yoong man beſmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with bloud, and ſo with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing reclaimed him to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, when as by all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood he was neare the brinke of the pit of death.</p>
            <p>Saint Paul alſo not onely lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and embraced Oneſimus being conuerted, who was an vnprofitable ſeruant, and fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue theefe, but maketh petition to his maſter, that he ſhould eſteeme him as himſelfe, &amp; that bicauſe he recanted. Theſe be the Apoſtles words,<note place="margin">Philem. from the 10. verſe to the 18.</note> I beſeech thee for my ſonne Oneſimus,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:26204:61"/> whom I haue begotten in my bonds. Which in time paſt was to thee vnprofitable, but now profitable both to thee &amp; to me, whom I haue ſent againe, thou therefore receiue him, that is mine owne bowels. Whom I would haue retained with me, that in thy ſtead he might haue miniſtred vnto me in the bonds of the Goſpell. But without thy mind, would I do nothing, that thy benefite ſhould not be as it were of neceſſitie, but willingly. It may be that he therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted for a ſeaſon, that thou ſhouldeſt receiue him for euer, not now as a ſeruant, but aboue a ſeruant, euen as a brother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, ſpecially to me; how much more then vnto thee, both in the fleſh and in the Lorde? If therfore thou accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our things common, receiue him, as my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle writeth to the Corrinthians touching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue ſinned, in this wiſe,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:26204:61"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſt when I come againe,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12, 22.</note> I ſhall bewaile many of them which haue ſinned already, and haue not repented of the vncleanes, and fornication, and wantonnes which they haue committed. And againe, I told you before,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13, 2.</note> and tell you before, if I come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I will not ſpare. You ſee then whom the Apoſtle bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and whom he wil not ſpare; not thoſe which haue ſinned, but thoſe which haue not repented, and not onely not repented, but once or twiſe admoniſhed of their faultes haue refuſed to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey. For in that he ſaith, I told you before, and tell you before, as though I had beene preſent the ſecond time, ſo write I now being abſent, he ſignifieth thus much, that being warned they contemned counſell.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe, I feare me, the ſame will fall out to vs; and although the ſame Paul, who threatned the Corinthians, be not at our elbowes, yet Chriſt is
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:26204:62"/> preſent, who ſpake by him, and if we perſeuer in hardnes of hart, he will ſay to vs, I will not ſpare you, not onely in the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but not in the time to come neither.<note place="margin">We must ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſinnes, and in confeſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to commit them againe, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſelues of remiſſion.</note> Wherfore let vs preuent his face by confeſſion, and let vs powre our our harts in his ſight,<note n="*" place="margin">Ecclus. 21, 1</note> Haſt thou ſinned? Saith the Scripture, do ſo no more, pray for thy fore-ſins, that they may be forgiuen thee. And againe,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou. 18, 17.</hi> Or, he that is first in his cauſe is iust.</note> The iuſt is an accuſer of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the beginning of his ſpeech. Let vs not then looke till our aduerſarie accuſe vs, but let vs preuent him by confeſſion, and ſo make the iudge more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable towards vs.</p>
            <p>And ſurely this I aſſuredlie know, thou confeſſeſt thy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and mourneſt for thy ſelfe, but this I do not alonely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of thee; for I would haue the amendment of the things to come ariſe, of the confeſſion of the things paſt, and ſo I would haue it done, that whileſt thou
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:26204:62"/> doeſt it, thou be aſcertained of forgiuenes. For euery one that doth ought, vnleſſe he know the thing he hath in hand will profit him, goeth about it, either care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, or not ſeriouſly. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; he that ſoweth ſeede, vnles he be ſure &amp; certaine there will be raine, that the earth will ſend foorth the blade, and that the fruite will ripen, he will neuer reape. And as none would faine ſpend labor in waſt, nor beſtow diligence in that which ſhall not be beneficiall vnto him: ſo he that ſoweth viſiens, teares, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion which is without hope vnprofitable, cannot ceaſe from ſinne, being holden faſt by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulitie. But as the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which hath no hope to reape fruite, careth not to driue off the birds from his corne, or beaſtes, or any other nociue things: right ſo he that ſoweth confeſſion with teares, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not it will be gainefull, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and driueth nothing from
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:26204:63"/> his hart, which may hurt repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Repentance is hurted, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one be enwrapped in ſuch euils as he was firſt;<note place="margin">Ecclus. 34, 24.</note> When one buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth &amp; another breaketh down, what profite haue they then (ſaith the ſcripture) but labour? And he that is purged from the touching of a corſe, and againe toucheth the dead, what auail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth waſhing? So he that faſteth to decline ſins, and goeth backe againe to them, who will heare his praiers?<note place="margin">Ecclus. 26, 29.</note> And again it is ſaid, when one departeth from righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes to ſinne, the Lorde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth ſuch to the ſword. And as a dog is odious that licketh vp his vomite againe,<note place="margin">Prou. 26, 11.</note> ſo is a foole, when he returneth to his tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p>So then this ſufficeth not, to accuſe thy ſelfe by declaring thy ſinnes, but do it with that zeale, that hope of iuſtification may proceede of repentance, and ſo you may bridle your ſoule to commit neuer the things again,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:26204:63"/> of which you haue made confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. One for to giue cenſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, is common to the faithfull and faithleſſe. Many enactors on ſtage which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnchaſt queanes &amp; whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers call them-ſelues ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and naughty folke, but not with purpoſe to amende, and therefore in very deed it is no confeſſion. For they ſpeak it not for griefe of hart, nor with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of teares, nor with hatred of the things they confeſſe, as if they could no more either hear or do the like, but the words be all the matter, which they lab out with their lips, not touched or pinched in minde, but after a ſort hunting for praiſe, through the elegancie and trimnes of ſpeech, which they vſe to their auditours. Neither are ſinnes ſo greeuous when they are colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably declared, as when indeed they are committed. Againe ſome are ſo benummed with ouer-great deſpaire, and are ſo
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:26204:64"/> deuoide of ſenſe, that making like account of good and ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, with great impudencie they diſcloſe their ſinnes, as though they were another bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. But I woulde haue thee to do nothing ſo, neither for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire to come to confeſſion, but with good and ſure hope of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes, the very roote of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire being cut off. Nowe the roote of diſpaire is ſloathfulnes, and not the roote onely but the nourſe to. For as a garment breedeth mothes, and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo;<note n="*" place="margin">A man is cauſed to think that any good thing is hard, and not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by him or any other through too great baſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: which when it ruleth in ones affection, he thinketh it may be eaſed by no good thing. And bicauſe ſlothfulnes is a certaine deiectiue penſiuenes of the ſpirit, it commeth to paſſe, that deſpaire ariſeth of ſloth. <hi>Thom. Aquin. lib. 2. ſ. p. q. 20. de deſper.</hi>
               </note> ſo ſloth doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone beget deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth and alſo foſtereth it. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they wax and grow togither, the one being cut off, the other (without queſtion) waneth and decreaſeth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeparate this link of ſinnes,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:26204:64"/> and breake their yoke. By the yoke of thy ſoule, I meane vice, whereto as it were a yoke, the life of man is tied: for when the thought of man is not right, the axle-tree of life is carried head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</p>
            <p>Harken yet what more we wil ſay. Often times it falleth out that a man amendeth many and great ſins by repentance, yet he committeth faultes after the good he hath wrought. And this is it, which laieth chiefely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire on the ſoule, bicauſe ſhe ſeemeth to pull downe that ſhe builded, and vainly to haue ſpent al hir trauell, this cogitation (I ſay) depriueth the ſoule of hope and confidence. Contrariwiſe we muſt thinke, what way this bad and hurtful thought may be expelled; namely, that vnleſſe the good we do, and the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gotten by repentaunce prohibited, &amp; were (as it were) a contrary weight to our ſinnes, there were no ſtay, but that we
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:26204:65"/> ſhoulde be carried downewarde into the depth of miſchiefe. And as a ſtrong habergeon ſuffereth not a kine and poiſoned dart to pierce the intrailes of the body, but in ſome part ſtoppeth the force thereof: ſo is it certaine, that he that carrieth hence ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good things and many bad, ſhall finde ſome eaſe in his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: and he that ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part without any goodnes, and with great ſtore of euill, what ſhoulde I ſpeake of his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? For there (queſtionles) good and had works ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, and ech (as it were) ſhall be ballanced, and the part that ſinketh, ſhall drawe with it the worker.<note place="margin">Rewards in the life to come of works both good and bad.</note> If the multitude of euils ſhall ouer-poiſe, it will pull the worker to hell; but if the good workes ſhall be greater, they will reſiſt and repugne againſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and will bring their worker to the place of the liuing, euen from the gate of hell. This is not phantaſtically imagined of my
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:26204:65"/> braine, the diuine Scriptures diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſent not from it, for thus the word of God ſpeaketh:<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 62, 12. Matt. 16, 27.</note> Thou rewardeſt euery one according to his worke. For not in hell one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in the kingdome of God,<note place="margin">Differences of ioies &amp; plagues in the life to come. Caluin. Institut, lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi> ſect. <hi>10</hi> Bulling. in Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. &amp; Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe. in <hi>41.</hi> verſ. cap. <hi>15. 1.</hi> Cor.</note> there ſhall be many differences.<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 14, 2.</note> In my fathers houſe (ſaith he) are many dwelling places. And againe:<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 15, 41.</note> There is another glory of the Sunne, and another glorie of the Moone. What is more wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, than that he ſheweth how exactly the meaſure of our deeds ſhall be weighed? One ſtar (ſaith he) differeth from another ſtar in glory, that by it he might ſhew that amongeſt all and euery one that ſhall be in that kingdome, there will be a difference. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſith we knowe all this, let vs not withdrawe our ſelues from good workes, neither yeelde to ſloth and ſluggardie, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of deſpaire. And admit we cannot attaine to the clearenes of the Sunne or Moone, yet we muſt deſire the brightnes of a
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:26204:66"/> ſtarre, howbeit inferior to them, let vs ſeeke at the leaſt for ſome light by our good deedes, let vs labour to be found worthie, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large ſomewhat the ſhining of heauen. If we cannot be gold, if we cannot be pretious ſtones, yet let vs be in ſtead of ſiluer, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let vs not be turned into that matter, which fire may conſume, that we be not found to be wood, hay, or ſtubble, let vs be euen the laſt in goodnes, not the firſt in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>By often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a little to a little, there will ariſe a great heape, as wittily ſaid Heſiodus,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </note> And as worldlie riches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, when euery ſmall gaine is regarded: ſo it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in heauenly riches, in increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the which no little good deede muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned.<note place="margin">Small good works conioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with faith &amp; repentance go not without reward.</note> Surely it is an abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, (ſeeing our Iudge doeth not denie a reward for<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 10.</note> a cup of cold water,) for vs to ſaye, that vnles we do great things, it will be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing auaileable. Yea this more I adde, that he that deſpiſeth not ſmall and little things, will by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:26204:66"/> &amp; little come to great things, and<note n="*" place="margin">Ecclus. 19, 1</note> he that contemneth ſmall things, (which concordeth with the Scripture) ſhall fall by little and little. And therfore I thinke for this cauſe, our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior did ordeine for ſmall things great rewardes. For what is leſſe, than to viſit the ſicke? And yet for this ſmall worke, he hath laid vp a great rewarde. And againe, what is ſo eaſie, as to giue the hungrie bread, the thirſtie drink, the naked raiment, and to ſeeke out him that is ſhut vp in priſon? Yet theſe things that be ſo little and ſmall, he reckeneth ſo great, as that he accounteth them mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred not to man, but to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and for them hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the celeſtiall kingdome.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (moſt dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) enter, enter the waie to eternall life, and put on againe<note n="*" place="margin">My yoke is light, and my burden is light This burden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not the weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of him that is loden, but the wings of him that flieth. For birds haue bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dens of their feathers, which on earth they beare, and them they are borne into the heauen. Augustin.</note> the yoke of Chriſt which is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:26204:67"/> and his burden which is light, recouer the vertues of thy mind, make thine ende like to thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, let not the treaſure of ſpirituall graces, gotten by ſuch labour, decaie; and they will ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily periſh, if thou perſiſt in euils, &amp; exaſperate the wrath of God againſt thy deedes. But before thou loſe much of thy treaſure, and before thy manured field be ſurrounded with hurtefull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luges, if thou exclude the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, and ſtop the ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſinne, thou maiſt bring it againe to his priſtine fertilitie, and by husbanding make it very battle.</p>
            <p>Ariſe therfore, ariſe and ſhake off the duſt from thee, ariſe from the earth, and ſtraightway (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue me) thine enimie will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid. For he threw thee downe, as though thou ſhouldeſt neuer riſe vp, but if he ſhall ſee thee to riſe from the earth, and lift thine eies towards the heauens, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent thy boldnes wil out-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:26204:67"/> him,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Reſist the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and he wil flie from you. Jam. <hi>4, 7.</hi> Jf one flie the diuell, he is a lion: if one reſiſt, he hath (for he is Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub, that is, a god of flies) no more power than a weake flie: according to the old verſe,
<q>
                        <l>Hóſtis non laedir, niſi cùm te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tátus obedit,</l>
                        <l>Eſt leo ſi cedis, ſi ſtas quaſi muſca recedit.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </note> &amp; the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thou art, the more fearefull he wilbe, and the more thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeſt, the more fraile and infirme thou makeſt him. Think alſo on this, that the more har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dineſſe God ſhall indue thee withal, the more hee will weaken both his boldneſſe and might.</p>
            <p>If ſo be thou haue affiance in my words, me thinketh I ſee to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee the mercy and aide of God, but thine aduerſarie to be affrighted by reaſon of ſhame and confuſion. Me thinketh I perceiue now in my mind, that with all gratefulnes and fauour euery virtue allureth thee to hir, hold on then earneſtly, labour chearefully, runne forward wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. Thou ſhalt find no want of me in that I can, but I will ſtill reaſon with thee in ſpeech, I wil continually exhort and ſtir thee
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:26204:68"/> vp, both preſent with liuely voice, and abſent with letters. Albeit I perſwade my ſelfe, if thou gladly read this I haue now written, there will be no cauſe, why thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſeeke for far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
            <trailer>Deo ſoli ſapienti, laus &amp; gloria.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_Christian_reader">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:26204:68"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the wicked woulde ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestlie conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of the daie of the Lord, it must needes be, that they woulde either wholie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſinne, or at leaſt, not ſo much be delighted therewith. Which Chryſoſtome right wel perceiued, for that ſo copiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo liuely (as it were with a pencile) he depainteth that day and time. On the other ſide, to ponder equally the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:26204:69"/> that in heauen abide for them, who in this life ſeek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chiefely the ſetting foorth of Gods glory, and the benefiting of their neighbor, who bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their ſinnes with true and vnfeined repentance, by the hand of faith lay hold on Gods promiſes, auaileth not a little, to the abandoning of ſinne and iniquitie. Wherefore (gentle Reader) in the ſentences fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing I haue vſed this order, that thoſe which apperteine to the ſeconde comming of Christ, and the puniſhment of the vngodly are ſet first, in the ſeconde place thoſe that ſhew the ioyes of the world to come, and in the last roome thoſe that teach, that by faith, ſincere repentance, and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of our liues, we may
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:26204:69"/> inioy that heauenly bliſſe. My petition to thee is this, that thou daine to accept my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, which if thou do, I ſhall be occaſioned to iudge my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell well bestowed. The Lorde of his mercy grant, that, ſith wickednes neuer more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor men neuer leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the comming of Christ vnto iudgement, we may hartily repent vs of our ſinnes, bicauſe the wrath of God hangeth ouer our heads: and that we may, as good Chriſtians, liue woorthy of our vocation, (liuing ſo as though euery one particularly ſhould ſay, with that holy man Saint Hierome, as often as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that day, euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my body quaketh: for whether I eate, or drinke, or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:26204:70"/> do any thing elſe, me thinketh alwaies that dreadfull trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſoundeth in mine eares, Ariſe O ye dead, and come to iudgement,) bicauſe the last houre is at hand. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>As deſirous of thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, as of his owne, in the Schoole of Chriſt Ieſus, R. WOL.</hi> OENIPODES. <hi>Non ciſtae, ſed pectori.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="extracts">
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:26204:70"/>
            <head>Sentences collected out of the Fathers works, <hi>which haue ſuch agreement</hi> with the former Treatiſe, as <hi>that they are not</hi> vnfit for this <hi>place.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the puniſhments of hell,</hi> and the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houre of the death of a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner,<note place="margin">Bernard. in ſpec. pec.</note> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately there will come euill ſpirits (like roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lions) to ſnatch away their pray. Then ſodainely ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the horrible places of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Chaos and obſcurity of darkenes, the dread of miſery and confuſion, the terror of that fearefull manſion, where is the place of weepers, where is the place of groners, where is the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:26204:71"/> voice of them that crie, WO, WO, Wo be to vs the children of Euah! When the miſerable ſoule departing from the body ſhall heare, ſee, and feele theſe and ſemblable thinges, yea a thouſand times worſe than may be ſpoken, in what (I pray,) how great, and how wonderous feare &amp; trembling ſhall ſhe be? What toong can vtter it, what booke declare it? What will now auaile the boaſting of knowledge, the pomp of the people, the vanity of the world, the greedines of earthly dignity? what ſhal then auaile the appetite of riot, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſnes of meate, exquiſite drinke, curioſitie of garmentes nicenes of the fleſh, gluttony of the belly, ſuperfluouſneſſe of foode, ſurfetting and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, curious building of houſes, poſſeſſion of terrene goods, ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping togither of prebends, hoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of riches? Whether can theſe thinges deliuer the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſoule of a man from the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:26204:71"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outh of the headious and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ble lion, that is, from the iawe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the curſed dragon.</p>
               <p>When that cunning decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,<note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> that ſonne of iniquitie, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt eager enimie of our ſoules, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>all miſerably and dreadfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eete with thy ſoule, how wilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou be able to abide the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll ſight of his terrible counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance, the intolerable ſtinke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is mouth, the brimſtone-like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames of his eies? How then wilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou be of force to abide ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat feare, of ſo horrible a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt? Be aſſured, that the feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f his dreadfull preſence, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth euery kinde of tormentes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich may be deuiſed in this world. At which the Prophet quaking betooke himſelfe to praier, ſaying, heare my praier O God when I call vpon thee, deliuer my ſoule from the feare of the enimie. He ſaide not from the power of the enimie, but from the feare of the enimy. But alas! my brother, if the ſinnefull
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:26204:72"/> ſoule be ſo much, and ſo greatly daunted at the ſight onely of ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than, how great confuſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> how great horror, how great af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fliction and how great lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall ſhe haue, through his touching and tormenting?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hierom. ad Heliod.</note>When the Lord ſhal be abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to iudge the ſorrowfull world, it ſhall make a great noiſe, and one kindred ſhall ſtrike the breaſt to another kindred. The kinges once moſt puiſſant, ſhall quake without a garde, fooliſh Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to with his ſchollers ſhall be brought foorth, then Ariſtotles arguments ſhall not be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, when that ſonne of the poore woman which exerciſed a craft ſhall come to iudge the endes of the earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">August. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de ſymb.</note>That iudge is neither preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with fauor, nor mooued with pittie, nor bribed with money, neither wil he be appeaſed with ſatisfaction, or repentance. Here let the ſoule deale for it ſelfe while it hath time, as long as
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:26204:72"/> there is a place for mercy, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there will be a place of iuſtice.</p>
               <p>In the laſt daie of iudgement,<note place="margin">Greg. hom. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> when the heauens beeing ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Angels miniſtring, the Apoſtles ſitting togither, Chriſt ſhall appeare in the ſeate of his maieſtie, all the elect and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſhall ſee him, that both the iuſt may reioice without ende of the gift of their reward, and the vniuſt euer lament, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengement of their plague.</p>
               <p>On the right hand there ſhall be our ſinnes to accuſe vs,<note place="margin">Anſel. de ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus mundi.</note> on the left hand infinite diuels, beneath the horrible confuſion of hell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue an angrie Iudge, without the worlde flaming, within our conſcience burning, there ſcarce the iuſt ſhall be ſaued. Alacke wretched ſinner, whither wilt thou flee? It is impoſſible to be hidden, intollerable to appeare.</p>
               <p>The ioie of the time preſent muſt be ſo vſed,<note place="margin">Greg. hom. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the bitternes of the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:26204:73"/> iudgement to come, may neuer depart from vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Of the ioies of heauen.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. lib. de morb.</note>SO great is the beautie of righteouſnes, ſo great is the ſweetenes of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting light, that is, of the immutable wiſedome, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we might not tarrie in it more than one daie, for this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone innumerable yeeres of this life repleniſhed with delights &amp; abundance of temporall goods, were not without cauſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be contemned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem lib. <hi>3.</hi> de ſymb.</note>We can eaſilier tel what there is not in that eternall life, than what there is. There is not deth, there is not mourning, there is not wearines, there is not weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, there is not hunger, there is no thirſt, no parching heate, no corruption, no lacke, no ſorrowe, no ſadnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem de vtil. agen. poenit.</note>Make haſte thither, where you may liue for euer. For if you
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:26204:73"/> ſo loue this miſerable and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie life, wherein you liue with ſuch labour, and wherein by run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, trauelling, ſweating, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, thou ſcarce get things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for the bodie: how much more ought you to loue the life euerlaſting, where you ſhall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine no labour, where alwaies is great quietnes, great felicitie, happie libertie, happie bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, where ſhall be fulfilled that the Lorde ſpake in the Goſpell, Men ſhal be like the Angels. And that, the iuſt ſhall ſhine, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Temporal life compared with eternall life,<note place="margin">Greg. in homil.</note> is rather to be called death than life. For the dailie fainting of corruption, what is it els, but a certaine longe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of death? But what tong can tell, or what vnderſtanding conceiue, how great thoſe ioies are of that ſupernall citie, to be in the aſſemblie of Angels, with the moſt bleſſed ſoules to ſtand by the glorie of the Creator, to behold in preſence the face of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:26204:74"/> God, to ſee that immeaſurable light, to feele no pangs of death, to inioy the gift of euer-induring incorruption.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Againſt deſpaire.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in lib. de ſymb.</note>THE theefe acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, Peter denied. In Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there is ſhewed, that no iuſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of himſelfe: in the theefe, that no wicked man being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, ſhould deſpaire. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the good feare, leaſt he periſh through pride, and let not the wicked deſpaire through much naughtines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem de vtil. agen. poen.</note>Let none deſpaire of Iudas the traitor; not ſo much the hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous wickednes which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, was the cauſe of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſtruction, as the deſpaire of forgiuenes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. ſup. Luc. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>Let none diſtruſt, let none in the priuitie of his old ſinnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of the rewardes of God. God knoweth how to change his
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:26204:74"/> determination, if thou know how to amend thy fault.</p>
               <p>Let no man deſpaire of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,<note place="margin">Iſido. de ſum. bon. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> although about the ende of his life, he be turned to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. God iudgeth euery one according to his end, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his life paſt.</p>
               <p>To commit ſome foule offence is the death of the ſoule:<note place="margin">Idem. ibid.</note> but to deſpaire, is to deſcend into hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Of Repentance.</head>
               <p>IF I proffer thee golde,<note place="margin">Ambr. in ſer de eleem. &amp; ieiun.</note> thou ſaieſt not, I will come to morrow, but at the inſtant thou requireſt it, none pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, none maketh excuſe: the redeeming of our ſoule is promiſed, and none maketh haſte. Conuerſion is neuer too late,<note place="margin">Hier. in ep. ad Laetam. Gregor. hom <hi>34.</hi> ſup. euan.</note> the theefe went from the croſſe to Paradiſe.</p>
               <p>There is greater ioy in heauen of a ſinner conuerted, than of a righteous man that ſtandeth: for a captaine alſo in war loueth
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:26204:75"/> that ſouldiour more, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned from flight hath valiantly ſlaine his foe, than him, that neuer fled, and hath neuer done any manly act. So the husbandman, loueth more that ground, which after thorns yeldeth foorth plentifull corne; than that which neuer had thornes, and neuer bare a fertile graine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. ep. <hi>3.</hi> ad Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</note>In nothing to ſin is onely the propertie of God, it is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of a wiſe man, both to correct his fault, and to repent for his ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hierom. in quod. ſerm.</note>With God not ſo much the meaſure of time, as the meaſure of griefe preuaileth, not ſo much the abſtinencie of meats, as the mortification of vices.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iſid. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de ſum. bon.</note>Repentance is the medicine of our wound, the hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which ſinners are ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by which God is prouoked to mercy. The which is not weighed by time, but by deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of lamentation and teares.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:26204:75"/>
               <p>O repentance,<note place="margin">Cyprian. de laud. poen.</note> what new thing ſhall I ſpeake of thee? Thou loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt al things which are bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou openeſt all things which are ſhut, thou mitigateſt all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, thou healeſt that is bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, thou enlumineſt that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, thou incourageſt all that is out of hope.</p>
               <p>Be not negligent bicauſe the Lord forbeareth you when you ſin,<note place="margin">Aug. in lib. de vtil. poen.</note> for how much the longer he waiteth that ye amend, ſo much the more greeuouſly will he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, if you be negligent.</p>
               <p>Better is a little bitternes in the cheekes,<note place="margin">Idem de <hi>10.</hi> chordis.</note> than a perpetuall torment in the bowels.</p>
               <p>Although the theefe was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in his latter end of all his ſinnes,<note place="margin">Id. de poen.</note> yet he gaue not an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to them that are baptized to ſinne, and perſeuer in euill. For then he was firſt baptized with the baptiſme of the ſpirit, in that then firſt he profeſſed Chriſt.<note place="margin">Hier. ſuper Matt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſweetenes of the apple recompenceth the ſowrenes of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:26204:76"/> the roote, the dangers of the ſea for hope of gaine delight vs, the hope of health aſſwageth the griefe of Phyſicke. He that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the kirnell, breaketh the nut, and he that will be partaker of euerlaſting goodnes, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſ. in ep. ad Heliod, Monach.</note>It is no great matter to fall in wreſtling, but to lie when one is caſt downe. It is not deadly to be wounded in battle: but after the wound is inflicted, through deſpaire to be cured, to denie a plaiſter to the bile. And often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we ſee wreſtlers crowned, after often ſlides, and manie downe-caſts. We ſee alſo a ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our after many flights to be a ſtout man, and to ouercome him that diſcomfited him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de ſpir. &amp; anima.</note>Behold the kingdome of God is to be ſolde; buy it if thou wilt. Neither thinke of ſome great thing for the greatnes of the price, it is woorth ſo much as thou haſt, ſeeke not what thou haſt, but what maner of bodie
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:26204:76"/> thou art. This thing is woorth ſo much as thou art, giue thy ſelfe and thou ſhalt haue it. But I am euill, thou wilt ſaie, and happily it will not receiue me, by giuing thy ſelfe vnto it thou ſhalt be good.</p>
               <p>That repentance is in vaine,<note place="margin">Idem in ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquijs.</note> which afterward a fault pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, lamentations profit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if ſinnes be doubled. It a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth nothing to craue pardon of euils, and anew to commit euils.</p>
               <p>He that knocketh his breaſt,<note place="margin">Idem in quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſerm.</note> and correcteth not himſelfe, ſtrengtheneth his ſins, and doth not take them away.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>NAZIANZENVS.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>Sícubi chalcógraphus titubârit lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor amice,</l>
                  <l>Da veniam, lapſo ſic petis ipſe tibi.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
